<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Baptist History | DuncanJohnson.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/categories/baptist-history/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-12T10:58:40-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Johnson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Notes - Baptists Through the Centuries by David Bebbington]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/12/03/book-notes-baptists-through-the-centuries-by-david-bebbington/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-03T15:47:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/12/03/book-notes-baptists-through-the-centuries-by-david-bebbington</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/12/tn_4850.png"></p>
<p>Bebbington, David W. <em>Baptists through the Centuries: A History of a Global People.</em> Waco, TX: Baylor University Press, 2010.</p>
<p>This book was runner-up in my textbook adoption process for my Baptist history course. I have not yet read this book in full, but I have found portions of this book to be helpful as I prepared lectures. I chose not to select this book as required course reading for two reasons:</p>
<ol type="a">
<li>Published as it is by Baylor University Press, it costs slightly more than Leonard.</li>
<li>Bebbington follows a <em>synthetic</em> rather than <em>chronological</em> approach to the details of Baptist history. He describes the synthetic approach in the paragraph quoted below.</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>“It is primarily a work of synthesis that attempts to put the pieces of the puzzle into an intelligible framework. Its approach, therefore, is topical. In accordance with the maxim that it is better to study problems rather than periods, each chapter addresses an issue in Baptist history. … A second feature of the book is its effort to set the problems at hand in a wider context than Baptist history. Baptists did not exist alone, and so the analysis gives space to the broader influences—intellectual, social, and political—that played on religious developments. … The third aspect worth mentioning is the principle of organization. Countries are not kept apart, for that misrepresents the reality of the past. For all the contrasts between different nations, Baptists traveled between them, read each other’s writings, and corresponded across oceans. What happened in one part of the world was often duplicated elsewhere.” (pp. 4–5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This approach is self-evident when you look at the chapter titles, listed below:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Introduction</li>
<li>Roots in the Reformation</li>
<li>Anabaptists and Baptists</li>
<li>Particular and General Baptists in the Seventeenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists and Revival in the Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Divisions among Baptists in the Nineteenth Century</li>
<li>Theological Polarization among Baptists</li>
<li>Baptists and the Social Gospel</li>
<li>Gospel and Race among Baptists</li>
<li>Women in Baptist Life</li>
<li>Church, Ministry, and Sacraments among Baptists</li>
<li>Baptists and Religious Liberty</li>
<li>Baptists and Foreign Mission</li>
<li>The Global Spread of the Baptists</li>
<li>Baptist Identity</li>
<li>Conclusion</li>
</ol>
<p>There is certainly plenty of merit for the use of a synthetic approach to historical study, and I’ve benefited immensely from reading other works that follow this approach (in fact, <em>Turning Points</em> by Noll is highly synchronic in some chapters). However, I don’t think a synthetic approach would work well for beginning students who had no general chronological framework into which to plug the disparate concepts a synthetic study would bring to the surface. However, for readers with a general familiarity with the Baptist story, Bebbington’s work may prove a refreshing approach. The synthetic approach is somewhat of a current trend in historiography, but I was encouraged to find that others share my relative antipathy towards it as a practice. For instance, John Aloisi (Assistant Professor of Historical Theology at Detroit Baptist Theological Seminary), gave the following recommendation for this book on <a href="http://dbts.edu/blog/learning-about-the-past-exploring-baptist-history/">his blog</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This book is a very interesting read…. Although described by the publisher as “a chronological survey” (back cover), Bebbington’s work is largely arranged in a topical format that can be be helpful though it also has the potential to be a bit disorienting at times. For example, I found it rather odd to read about William Carey almost 100 pages after Walter Rauschenbusch when Carey was born exactly 100 years before Rauschenbusch. Similarly, the book includes a chapter titled “Women in Baptist Life” (ch. 10). I wondered, why not just discuss key Baptist women at appropriate points in the historical narrative (e.g., in the first nine chapters)? I don’t see a compelling reason for making that topic a distinct chapter. A similar observation could be made about the chapter on religious liberty (ch. 12). On the other hand, if one wants to read an insightful chapter on these topics or on things like Baptists and the social gospel (ch. 8) or Baptists and race relations (ch. 9), Bebbington is a very good place to turn. Overall, Bebbington’s work is definitely helpful and well worth reading, but the potential reader should realize that Bebbington doesn’t tell the story of Baptist history in anything like a chronological narrative. So I’m recommending it with the caveat that if you like to read history in a generally chronological format, Bebbington may drive you crazy. But if you want to read about some key topics in Baptist history, this is a helpful book by a first rate historian.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So anyway, if you’re glazed over with all this rambling about historiography, let me just bring this back to a point of usefulness by sharing Bebbington’s own statements summing up the overall point of the book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“This book attempts to address the question of who Baptists have been over the four centuries of their existence. It tries to take account of ways in which they adapted to the societies in which they lived as well as their central practices. … [I]t must not be assumed that Baptists possessed a single, consistent identity. There were, after all, many types of Baptists. … The variety of Christian bodies called ‘Baptist’ has to be taken into account. So does the consideration that there was great deal of change over time. The circumstances of the early seventeenth century, when Baptists first arose, were very different from those of the early twenty-first century. It was a hallmark of the denomination to be strongly attached to the Bible, but ways of understanding the place of scripture in ordering church life altered over the centuries. Again there was much variation over space.” (p. 2)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The coverage of this book extends not just over England in the period from 1609 to the present but also over the world at large. … There is, therefore, a need for Baptist history to have an international dimension. Because research on many countries (including some of the nations just mentioned) is at a very preliminary stage, there are all too many gaps in the coverage of the present volume. The aim here is not to deal with every country where Baptists have existed, but to discuss broad trends with representative instances.” (pp. 3-4)</p>
</blockquote>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Readings in Baptist History: Four Centuries of Selected Documents by Joe Early]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/02/12/book-review-readings-in-baptist-history-four-centuries-of-selected-documents-by-joe-early/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-12T13:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/02/12/book-review-readings-in-baptist-history-four-centuries-of-selected-documents-by-joe-early</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/02/early.jpg" alt="Readings in Baptist History by Joe Early" /><figcaption>Readings in Baptist History by Joe Early</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Early, Joseph. <em>Readings in Baptist History: Four Centuries of Selected Documents.</em> Nashville, TN: B&amp;H Academic, 2008. ISBN 9780805446746. 288 pages.</p>
<p>Available for purchase from:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=446746">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0805446745/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0805446745&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca (Canada)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0805446745/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0805446745&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20">Amazon.com (USA)</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>By necessity, the study of history requires the perusal of historic texts. By devoting attention to primary sources, the student learns from the perspective of eyewitnesses and participants. Sometimes reading primary sources uncovers the student’s own bias; at other times it presents the biases of the original actors in their own context. In studying any historical period or genre, beginning students oftentimes ignore important primary sources, not necessarily from lack of interest, but because those texts are scattered in various locations. A common remedy for this problem is a sourcebook, a published edition of key primary sources on a given topic. Joseph Early’s <em>Readings in Baptist History</em> provides an up-to-date sourcebook of key Baptist texts in one affordable volume.</p>
<p>This work fills a largely overlooked niche in the literature on Baptist history. In his preface, Early observes that although several books on Baptist history have appeared since H. Leon McBeth’s <em>Baptist Heritage: Four Centuries of Baptist Witness</em> in 1987, no new sourcebook has been produced since the 1990 release of McBeth’s companion volume, <em>A Sourcebook for Baptist Heritage.</em> In this work, Early adds newer documents while also including “seminal older documents” (v) to provide a comprehensive update.</p>
<p>In selecting texts for inclusion, Early seeks “to provide as broad a scope and be as inclusive as possible” (vi). As a result, representative texts from a variety of Baptist traditions appear within the collection, including “British Baptists, Black Baptists, American Baptists, Southern Baptists, Russian Baptists, Landmark Baptists, and Fundamental Baptists” (vi). Of course, selecting key texts to include means that some texts must be excluded, and Early notes that his selections were limited by word count and the interests of his intended audience of “students of Baptist history” (vi).</p>
<p>The selections in the book are organized chronologically, beginning with texts from the exiled English General Baptists led by John Smyth and Thomas Helwys in 1609. The book exhibits a generally even distribution of texts over the course of Baptist history, with seven chapters from the seventeenth century, eight from the eighteenth century, twelve from the nineteenth century, and fourteen from the twentieth century. A complete chapter listing is included below this review for those interested in the details.</p>
<p>One editorial decision is unfortunate, though based on admirable motives. In the interest of appealing to a broad readership, there are no editorial introductions to the various texts included in the work. Early indicates that he chose not to include comments on individual texts so that he would not “color the interpretation of the documents” (vi). Unfortunately, this means that students sometimes struggle to understand the significance and place of the documents within the broader context of Baptist history.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most significant contribution of the book is that it includes documents relevant to the theological controversy within the Southern Baptist Convention. In the chapter that includes the Baptist Faith and Message, the three different versions (1925, 1963, 2000) are presented in three parallel columns for easy comparison.</p>
<p>My own students reacted to the book quite positively, although at first they seemed unexcited by the prospect of reading a collection of source texts. As their background knowledge of the Baptist story developed over the semester, they became more interested in the readings. By the end of the semester, some of my students were saying that they enjoyed reading Early even more than their other textbook.</p>
<p>For a bibliography of supplemental readings, see <a href="http://www.baptisttheology.org/book-reviews/readings-in-baptist-history">the review by Jason G. Duesing of Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
<!-- more -->
<hr />
<p><em>List of Chapters</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Character of the Beast, 1609</li>
<li>Letter to Sir William Hammerton, 1609</li>
<li>A Declaration of Faith of English People Remaining in Amsterdam in Holland, 1611</li>
<li>A Short Declaration of the Mystery of Iniquity, 1612</li>
<li>The Beginnings of the Particular Baptists and the Birth of Immersion, 1633</li>
<li>The Bloudy Tennent of Persecution, 1644</li>
<li>The Whipping of Obadiah Holmes, 1651</li>
<li>The Power of the Association, 1749</li>
<li>The Birth of the Charleston Association, 1751</li>
<li>Birth of the Sandy Creek Baptist Association, 1758</li>
<li>A Body of Doctrinal and Practical Divinity, 1769</li>
<li>An Appeal to the Public for Religious Liberty, 1773</li>
<li>Black Baptists</li>
<li>The Rights of Conscience Inalienable, 1791</li>
<li>An Enquiry, 1792</li>
<li>The “Wall of Separation”</li>
<li>Formation of the English Baptist Union, 1813</li>
<li>Address at the Formation of the Triennial Convention, 1814</li>
<li>Treatise on Slavery, 1822</li>
<li>Primitivism and the Antimission Movement</li>
<li>Report and Warning about Campbellism, 1830</li>
<li>The Georgia Test Case and the Alabama Resolutions</li>
<li>Southern and Northern Perspectives on the 1845 Schism</li>
<li>Address Explaining Why the Southern Baptist Convention was Organized, 1845</li>
<li>Old Landmarkism: What is It?</li>
<li>A Letter from China</li>
<li>Another Word Concerning the Down-Grade</li>
<li>The Baptist World Alliance</li>
<li>The Kingdom of God, 1917</li>
<li>Baptists and Religious Liberty, 1920</li>
<li>The Impact of J. Frank Norris on Baptist Life</li>
<li>The Cooperative Program, 1924</li>
<li>The Trail of Blood, 1931</li>
<li>The Baptist Way, 1945</li>
<li>Russian Baptist History from 1929 to 1963, 1967</li>
<li>Origins of the Conservative Resurgence</li>
<li>The Resurgence of Calvinism</li>
<li>Peace Committee Report, 1987</li>
<li>Doctrinal Statement of the Baptist Missionary Association of America, 1989</li>
<li>The Cooperative Baptist Fellowship</li>
<li>The Baptist Faith and Message, 1925, 1963, 2000</li>
</ol>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Baptist Ways: A History by Bill Leonard]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/01/16/book-review-baptist-ways-a-history-by-bill-leonard/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/01/16/book-review-baptist-ways-a-history-by-bill-leonard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/01/leonard.jpg" alt="Baptist Ways by Bill Leonard" /><figcaption>Baptist Ways by Bill Leonard</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Leonard, Bill J. <em>Baptist Ways: A History.</em> Valley Forge, PA: Judson Press, 2003. ISBN 9780817012311. xiv + 464 pages.</p>
<p>Available for purchase from:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=012311">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0817012311/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0817012311&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca (Canada)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0817012311/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0817012311&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20">Amazon.com (USA)</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>Conceived as a replacement for Robert Torbet’s well-known text, <em>A History of the Baptists</em>, this book attempts to survey the worldwide history of Baptists from their origins in seventeeth-century England. Leonard states his thesis clearly in the opening paragraph of his preface:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The thesis of this book is relatively simple. It suggests that amid certain distinctives, Baptist identity is configured in a variety of ways by groups, subgroups, and individuals who claim the Baptist name. This identity extends across a theological spectrum from Arminian to Calvinist, from conservative to liberal, from open to closed communionist, and from denominationalist to independent.” (xi)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This thesis allows Leonard to include a broad survey of individuals and groups, including giving significant attention to the role of women and minorities in the history of the Baptists. One interesting feature is regular description of Baptist hymnody and worship. Throughout the work, Leonard draws primarily from secondary sources, although the notes (which are placed as endnotes after each chapter) indicate a measured use of primary sources.</p>
<p>The book alternates between chronological and geographical perspectives. Chapter 1 provides a standard introduction to the study of Baptist history, surveying common doctrinal distinctives and contrasting the three views of Baptist origins. Chapters 2–9 proceed chronologically, telling the story of English and American Baptists from their obscure seventeenth-century beginnings to national prominence during the nineteenth-century. Chapters 10–14 survey the Baptist movement elsewhere, giving the book a global scope. For instance, chapter 10 provides a concise summary of Baptists in Canada (227–244), followed by brief sections on Baptist efforts in various Latin American countries. These chapters will be of most interest to readers outside the United States, but are important for all readers to provide a full understanding of the various kinds of Baptists to be found throughout the world. Chapters 15 and 16 resume the story of Baptists in the West during the twentieth century.</p>
<p><em>Chapters</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Baptist Ways: Defining a People</li>
<li>Baptist Beginnings: The Historical Context</li>
<li>English Baptists: The Seventeenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: Beginnings</li>
<li>English Baptists: The Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: The Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in Britain: The Nineteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: 1800-1845</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: 1845-1900</li>
<li>Baptists in the Americas and the Caribbean</li>
<li>African American Baptists</li>
<li>Baptists in Greater Britain</li>
<li>Baptists in Europe</li>
<li>Baptists in Africa and Asia</li>
<li>Baptists in the British Isles and Europe: The Twentieth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: The Twentieth Century</li>
</ol>
<!-- Omit following paragraph... not sure I have the right examples, although I know I felt this way at various points in the book. Too bad I didn't mark it. -->
<!-- Due to the broad scope of the book, Leonard frequently mentions names and events without remarking on their significance. Examples of this include his mention of Benoi Stinson (211--212) and James Manning (231). Without  -->
<p>Predictably, the book reflects the denominational affiliation of its publisher, Judson Press. As the <a href="http://www.judsonpress.com/home_about_us.cfm">publishing arm of the American Baptist Churches USA</a>, Judson Press represents a particular constituency of Baptists. The book puts some emphasis on this strain of Baptist identity, tracing the development of the ABCUSA out of the Northern Baptist Convention in some detail in chapter 16.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the book omits or downplays some important events in Southern Baptist history. For instance, the extensive controversy over the modernism of Crawford H. Toy receives no treatment. Toy, though he was professor at The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary from 1869–1879, is only mentioned as a missionary appointee to Japan who “never went because the [Foreign Mission Board] delayed all appointments in anticipation of the Civil War and related economic difficulties” (353). The dates of his professorship at Southern appear only in an otherwise unremarkable parenthesis, and there is no mention of his broken engagement to missionary Lottie Moon. As <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/30149574">other reviewers</a> <a href="http://www.baptisttheology.org/book-reviews/baptist-ways-a-history/">have noted</a>, the Conservative Resurgence in the SBC also receives scant coverage, appearing only in summary on pages 414–415.</p>
<p>Occasionally, the book suggests that an emphasis on biblical literalism results in erratic or erroneous conclusions. An early example of this pattern occurs in the treatment of John Smyth, the early sixteenth-century Baptist. Smyth was certainly unstable, following a spiritual trajectory that parallels that of Roger Williams in America. Smyth began as an Anglican until he adopted Separatist views. Later, he founded the General Baptists along with Thomas Helwys by baptizing himself and then his own followers. This self-baptism brought criticism, and eventually Smyth repudiated his own baptism and sought admission into a nearby Mennonite sect. The book attributes Smyth’s restlessness to his commitment to the Bible: “His biblicism took him through many Protestant communities in a search for the fullest revelation available” (25). Smyth was undoubtedly a biblicist, but there are other explanations for his repudiation of his self-baptism. On occasion, the book suggests that biblicism leads to other negative results, which will disappoint conservative readers.</p>
<p>Other reviews have been mixed in their final appraisal of Leonard’s text, despite the unanimous acknowledgement that producing a one-volume Baptist history is a difficult task. As a potential course textbook, the work suffers from a lack of visual aids (a deficiency that equally applies to the competing volumes by Torbet and McBeth). Other complaints include the slightly negative treatment of more conservative Baptist traditions and the deliberately international focus of chapters 10–16. On the other hand, these two complaints illustrate and, to some degree, substantiate Leonard’s thesis that Baptists are a broadly differentiated sect. As a potential textbook for a course on Baptist history, I find Leonard’s text to be useful despite these perceived weaknesses. This is especially true for me as I teach the history of the Baptists outside of the United States of America. Although Leonard’s book should not be the only volume that students of the Baptists consult, I am convinced that it is a worthy member of the body of literature on the topic.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Student Work Showcase: Baptist History Timeline]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/12/06/student-work-showcase-baptist-history-timeline/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-06T11:08:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/12/06/student-work-showcase-baptist-history-timeline</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/Baptist-History/"><img src="/images/2013/11/timeline.png" alt="Baptist History Timeline project" /></a></p>
<p>This semester, students in my Baptist History class were responsible for a group project to construct an <a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/Baptist-History/">online timeline</a> of key events in the history of the Baptist movement. It has been rather interesting to watch this project develop as the students submitted events and presented their findings to the class. Since my students submitted their final entries this week, I thought I’d share their work, write down my observations on the project as a classroom assignment, and note some ideas I’ve had for ways to use this in the future.</p>
<!-- more -->
<h2 id="thoughts-on-educational-value">Thoughts on Educational Value</h2>
<p>As an assignment, I found that this was a useful project in several ways.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>It created interest in the course by allowing students to explore areas of interest. Some of my students said that they didn’t like the class at first, but as a result of the project it was now one of their favorite classes.</li>
<li>It encouraged my students to read widely from the literature.</li>
<li>The atomistic nature of the assignment (30 separate timeline entries submitted in smaller assignments over the semester) was less intimidating than a 10-20 page paper on a single topic. This makes it an interesting project for a survey class, as it allows students with no prior knowledge or interest to expand their knowledge in any direction they choose.</li>
<li>It forced my beginning history students to grapple with questions of significance as they analyzed historical events. In selecting events for their timeline contributions, students had to decide whether an event was truly significant for the grand story of the Baptists throughout history. Sometimes they made good choices and sometimes they didn’t, but the exercise itself helped to introduce them to the basics of selecting and evaluating evidence.</li>
</ol>
<p>Of course, there are some inherent weaknesses too.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Because it focuses on dates and data, the project doesn’t require the construction of a coherent argument or narrative. My goal was to supplement this deficiency through reading assignments and lectures, and to some extent student performance on assessments suggests that this actually worked.</li>
<li>Because students come to the project with limited knowledge, their choices tend to reflect inherent prejudices and/or emphases from class lectures.</li>
<li>Because students were required to submit a specific quota of events, they did not always select truly significant events. I tried to reflect that in my marks for their assignments, but overall I’m happy with the results of their work.</li>
<li>Because it emphasizes finding separate events, it tends to result in superficial knowledge rather than deep comprehension.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are probably other observations I could make on the effect of this assignment, but this is enough for now. In summary, I thought it was a worthwhile project and a useful student assignment which I’ll repeat in future offerings of this class.</p>
<h2 id="ideas-for-future-implementation">Ideas for Future Implementation</h2>
<p>This sort of project is something I’ve done by myself a few times before. Examples of my own efforts this way can be found on my <a href="/projects/">Projects page</a>. As I review the events which my students chose for their contributions, there are a number of things I would probably do differently.</p>
<p>I have plenty of ideas for things that I could do with this project at some later date. These ideas roughly break down into three areas: 1) pedagogy, 2) content and 3) technical.</p>
<h3 id="pedagogy">Pedagogy</h3>
<p>One oversight in my project definition was any reference to grammar, spelling, and capitalization. I shouldn’t need to worry about this at this level, but the simple reality is that my students tend to struggle with these things. This should factor into their marks, but it didn’t for this class because my expectations were too idealistic.</p>
<h3 id="content">Content</h3>
<p>At some point, I’d like to take my students’ contributions, edit them, and put them into a fresh dataset that represents my own perspective on the history of Baptists. If I ever do this, I will keep the appropriate “Contributor” attribute in the dataset to acknowledge the original work of my students. In many ways, their submissions exhibit a level of passion that my own timeline projects have never had.</p>
<p>If I ever do that, here are some things I would change:</p>
<ul>
<li>I’d place less focus on individuals and organizations and more focus on concrete events. Although many of the individuals/organizations my students selected are important, I’m not sure that representing the duration of some of these peoples’ lives is truly significant for the full story of the Baptists. Some individuals truly were significant over the course of their life, such as Charles Spurgeon and William Carey. Others, though, are perhaps better remembered for a few accomplishments than for a lifetime of significant efforts, such as perhaps Benoi Stinson or Sarah Cummings.</li>
<li>I’d reorganize the events under a more uniform set of categories that are defined in terms of specific chronological periods. At the beginning, I defined only three simple categories for my students: “English Particular Baptists,” “English General Baptists,” and “Baptists in America.” These categories are really only useful for telling the story of Baptists from their founding in the 1600s until around the end of the 18th century. After that, those categories become rather clunky. For instance, “Baptists in America” would probably make more sense if I changed it to “Baptists in America before 1845.” After 1845, I’d need to create separate categories for Northern and Southern Baptists, as well as other groups of Baptists that developed after that time.</li>
<li>I’d edit my student entries to only include the most significant entries. In other words, in producing my own dataset based on their contributions, I’d filter out the submissions that where significance is questionable. I’d still retain their work in a data file that includes all the entries made by that particular class, but not all of those entries would make it into my edited version of the dataset.</li>
<li>I’d also supplement student contributions to correct for lacunae. My students did some admirable work on this project, and in many cases identified truly significant events to display. However, they still missed a few truly significant things, either due to a lack of knowledge or interest. For instance, one of my students included several of Adoniram Judson’s wives, but not one of my students thought to create an entry for Adoniram Judson himself.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="technical">Technical</h3>
<p>This project depends on code (specifically, the <a href="http://simile-widgets.org/">Simile Exhibit Timeline plugin</a>). As a result, there are always technical things that need maintenance, as well as technical opportunities that could be explored. Someday, here are some things that I’d love to get done to make this sort of project more useful.</p>
<ul>
<li>Change the lens design to include links to copies of the original text of a document when available in a similar way to the wikipedia links.</li>
<li>Implement multiple datasets so the same code can be reused for each class where I give this as an assignment.</li>
<li>Upgrade the timeline code to take advantage of improvements in Simile Exhibit 3.0 (or one of the newer implementations that can be found in the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/simile-widgets">SIMILE Widgets Google Group</a>). Apparently there are <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4700419/alternative-to-simile-timeline-for-timeline-visualization">other projects out there that do similar things</a> (some of which may even work better), but I’m too heavily invested in the Simile Exhibit framework to be interested in switching to an alternate platform right now.</li>
<li>Develop a better system for submitting entries that supports image upload and supports additional file formats (SVG was a problem). I’m not completely sure how I would set this up. Ultimately, I’d probably need to set up access to Amazon S3 storage, but there’s no way to easily incorporate that into my current system where students submit entries via a Google Spreadsheets form and can immediately see the results on the timeline itself.</li>
<li>Implement geo-code support within the timeline dataset, and then implement functionality to switch between timeline view and map view. Because geo-code data requires advanced technical skills to generate, this is not something I would require students to submit but would be nice to have in edited versions of the dataset.</li>
</ul>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Historical roots of local-church-onlyism]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/11/05/historical-roots-of-local-church-onlyism/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-05T13:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/11/05/historical-roots-of-local-church-onlyism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’d like to add a few comments on an interesting debate over at my Dad’s blog about the New Testament’s use of the term translated “church” (<em>ekklesia</em>).</p>
<ul>
<li>In <a href="http://oxgoad.ca/2013/10/22/ekklesia/">one post</a>, he argues that the biblical usage of the term “church” suggests that there is such a thing as the “universal church,” defined as “a universal body of believers that includes all believers from all ages in one spiritual union, the church.”</li>
<li>In a <a href="http://oxgoad.ca/2013/10/27/ekklesia-part-2/">followup</a>, he goes further, demonstrating from biblical texts that the word is also used for what we call the “visible church,” inclusive of the sum total of professing believers on earth.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="why-does-this-matter">Why does this matter?</h2>
<p>Suggesting that the word “church” can mean anything other than a “local church” can get you into trouble with some Baptists, and so an interesting discussion broke out in the comments on both posts. In the comments, my Dad asks one question for his local-church-only interlocutors: <strong>“Why is the idea of local church only so important? Or, to put it another way, why is the idea of the universal church dangerous?”</strong></p>
<h2 id="ideas-and-consequences">Ideas and Consequences</h2>
<p>I’d like to suggest one reason why local-church-only advocates cannot concede the existence of the universal church. (Of course, doing so requires that they ignore the plain reading of texts such as Ephesians 1:22–23, but for the exegesis I refer you again to <a href="http://oxgoad.ca/2013/10/22/ekklesia/">the original post</a>.) <!-- more --> The idea that the term “church” can only refer to a local assembly is simply a necessary corollary of Landmarkist theology. Landmarkism depends on an uninterrupted succession of local assemblies to support the theory that the “true church” comprises the Baptist tradition throughout the ages. This (widely discredited) view of history is known as Baptist successionism.</p>
<p>If a Landmarkist allows for a universal aspect to the church, he implies that genuine believers might be found outside of the supposed succession of local churches (the “Baptists”) but within the scope of Christendom (including medieval Catholics).</p>
<p>Because the Landmarkist is predisposed to avoid that conclusion, he must go to great lengths to justify a local-only view of the church. Seen in this light, the local-only view becomes nothing more than part of an artificial perimeter around the Landmarkist theory.</p>
<h2 id="historical-evidence">Historical Evidence</h2>
<p>If the explanation above is correct, we would expect to find the idea that the local-church-only idea in the writings of the early Landmarkists. Today, I ran across some evidence that confirms that early Landmarkists indeed believed that the Bible does not allow for a universal or invisible church.</p>
<figure>
<img src="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/th106-2013/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2013/08/220px-JamesRobinsonGraves.jpg" title="J. R. Graves" alt="J. R. Graves" /><figcaption>J. R. Graves</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>J. R. Graves was not the first to hold Landmarkism, but he was certainly one its most vociferous early proponents. Through his influence, successionist historiography and Landmark ecclesiology became a significant force within American Baptist circles.</p>
<p>In Leon McBeth’s history of the Baptist movement, he notes that Graves believed the church to be “a single congregation, complete in itself, independent of all other bodies, civil or religious, … amenable only to Christ.”<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a> He thought that the “invisible church” was nothing more than “invisible nonsense.” In a more extended quote, Graves argues that</p>
<blockquote>
<p>the only church that is revealed to us is a visible church, and the only church with which we have anything to do, or in connection with which we have any duties to perform, is a visible body…. Christ never set up but one kingdom; and if this is visible, he has no invisible kingdom or church, and such a thing has no real existence in heaven or earth. It is only an invention to bolster up erroneous theories of ecclesiology.<a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"><sup>2</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="evaluation">Evaluation</h2>
<p>In evaluating Graves’ statements, this quote from Sidney Ahlstrom is telling.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At the heart of Graves’s argument was a doctrine of the Kingdom which allowed a syllogism to do the work of historical research: the Kingdom has prevailed; the Kingdom must always have included true churches; Baptist churches are the only true churches; therefore, Baptist churches have always existed.<a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"><sup>3</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>As an historical theory, successionism is bankrupt because it is based on an absence of evidence. Likewise, the view that the New Testament only speaks of the local church requires us to ignore clear biblical evidence. It seems to me that the only reason to hold this view is to support the scaffold for the rest of Landmark theology.</p>
<section class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>J. R. Graves quoted in Leon McBeth, <em>The Baptist Heritage</em> (Nashville, TN: Broadman Press, 1987), 450–451.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Ibid., 451.<a href="#fnref2">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Sydney E. Ahlstrom, <em>A Religious History of the American People</em> (New Haven, Conn.: Yale Univ. Press, 1972), 723.<a href="#fnref3">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
