<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[DuncanJohnson.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-14T14:34:00-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/</id>
  <author>
	<name><![CDATA[Duncan Johnson]]></name>
	
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Proudly Powered by Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Doctrine of Assurance]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/11/08/doctrine-of-assurance/"/>
	<updated>2014-11-08T22:05:00-07:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/11/08/doctrine-of-assurance</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This Sunday in my Adult Sunday School class, I’ll be taking advantage of a scheduled break in our <a href="http://www.meadowlandsbaptist.ca/resources/adult-bible-study-notes/">regular teaching schedule</a>. We just finished teaching through First, Second, and Third John last week, and will be beginning a study of John’s Gospel on November 16. To take advantage of the break in between books, I plan to focus on a topic that frequently arises in 1 John: assurance of salvation.</p>
<p>In the Sunday School class, we’ll be working through a number of Bible passages as they are presented in chapter 40 of Wayne Grudem’s <em>Systematic Theology: An Introduction to Biblical Doctrine</em> (available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0310286700/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0310286700&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0310286700/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0310286700&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20&amp;linkId=KLSMSU5FI4DCES5J">Amazon.com</a>, or <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=620882">CBD</a>). His organization is helpful, and I find his comments on Hebrews 6:4–12 particularly useful. I’d recommend this chapter to anyone who is interested in a thorough understanding of Scripture on this topic.</p>
<p>Another helpful resource is a brief blog series from Tim Challies. While I wouldn’t express everything exactly as he did, of course, his thoughts are helpful (and free!):</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="http://www.challies.com/articles/sincerity-and-assurance-of-salvation">Sincerity and Assurance of Salvation</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.challies.com/articles/assurance-of-salvation-part-2">Assurance of Salvation (Part 2)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.challies.com/articles/assurance-of-salvation-part-3">Assurance of Salvation (Part 3)</a></li>
</ol>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Rediscovering the Church Fathers by Michael Haykin]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/14/book-review-rediscovering-the-church-fathers-by-michael-haykin/"/>
	<updated>2014-10-14T16:59:00-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/14/book-review-rediscovering-the-church-fathers-by-michael-haykin</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/10/7260060-L.jpg" alt="Rediscovering the Church Fathers" /><figcaption>Rediscovering the Church Fathers</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Haykin, Michael A. G. <em>Rediscovering the Church Fathers: Who They Were and How They Shaped the Church.</em> Wheaton: Crossway, 2011. ISBN 9781433510434. 172 pages. Includes index.</p>
<p>In this book, Haykin combines his remarkable knowledge of the earliest period of church with his zeal for heart-warming devotional Christianity to produce a work that both informs and edifies.</p>
<p>Haykin writes to counter the fact that, in his view, “far too many modern-day evangelicals are either ignorant of or quite uncomfortable with the church fathers” (13). In this regard, he observes, that “<em>certain</em> strains of anti-intellectual fundamentalism have discouraged an interest in that ‘far country’ of church history” (14, my emphasis). He understands that this problem is not entirely due to bad reasons, however, because our “desire to be ‘people of the Book’—an eminently worthy desire—has also led to a lack of interest in other students of Scripture from that earliest period of the church’s history after the apostolic era” (14). Despite this trend, Haykin argues that we should read the church fathers for several reasons. We should read them for “freedom and wisdom,” to understand the New Testament, because of bad press about them, to aid in defending the faith, and for spiritual nurture. In the book, Haykin’s goal is to spark our interest in reading more of the fathers “by looking at several case studies, as it were” (29). These case studies serve to introduce important themes in both the early history of the church and the development of cardinal doctrines. As such, this book is not a comprehensive survey of the fathers, a feature that is apparent by the fact that although there are chapters on many important fathers, some of the most important (like Athanasius and Augustine) are actually left out.</p>
<p>Table of Contents:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Rediscovering the Church Fathers: A Vital Need for Evangelicals</li>
<li>Dying for Christ: The Thought of Ignatius of Antioch</li>
<li>Sharing the Truth: <em>The Letter to Diognetus</em></li>
<li>Interpreting the Scripture: The Exegesis of Origen</li>
<li>Being Kissed: The Eucharistic Piety of Cyprian and Ambrose</li>
<li>Being Holy and Renouncing the World: The Experience of Basil of Caesarea</li>
<li>Saving the Irish: The Mission of Patrick</li>
<li>Walking with the Church Fathers: My First Steps on a Lifelong Journey</li>
</ol>
<p>Appendix 1: Reading the Fathers: A Beginner’s Guide Appendix 2: Reflections on Jaroslav Pelikan, <em>The Emergence of the Catholic Tradition (100–600)</em></p>
<p>I would like to share just a few comments on how some of these chapters impacted me, without going into a summary of each individual chapter or a discussion of major themes that build throughout the book.</p>
<p>Many (if not all) of these chapters nurtured me spiritually. One of Haykin’s many research interests is the study of Christian spirituality, a topic that is the focus of a festschrift in his honor titled <em>The Pure Flame of Devotion: The History of Christian Spirituality</em> (edited by Weaver and Clary). This emphasis shines throughout the book, but I was particularly encouraged by Ignatius’ steadfast anticipation of his own martyrdom and Patrick’s dogged commitment to evangelizing his former captors in western Ireland.</p>
<p>As I expected, many of the chapters deepened my appreciation for the precise formulations of orthodoxy that we enjoy as a result of the diligent efforts forged by these men in times of doctrinal controversy. The chapters on the <em>Letter to Diognetus</em> and Basil of Caesarea were especially helpful in that regard.</p>
<p>On another note, my understanding was transformed by his chapter on Origen. I did not realize it, but I had allowed bad press on the Fathers to distort my understanding of their abilities. I began reading the chapter assuming that Origen’s famous penchant for allegory would mean that there would be little for me to learn about biblical interpretation. But I realized that my understanding of Origen was tinted by a gross misunderstanding. Rather than reading about a half-crazed mystic who simply allowed his imagination to run wild whenever he encountered something he didn’t immediately understand in the biblical text, I learned that Origen was a deeply devoted student of Scripture who understood that allegorical interpretations were not always appropriate (81–82). In fact, Origen actually affirmed three uses for the literal meaning of Scripture, rather than seeing it all as a deeply spiritual parable of something other than what it actually says, and said that the interpreter “should not resort too easily” to allegory (84). Although Origen is perhaps the best-known implementer of the patristic penchant for allegory, he only employed it when he felt it was appropriate, and he articulated principles for the appropriate use of allegory (85–86). Coming away from this chapter, I realized that I have misunderstood the church fathers and their use of allegory because I had not been listening to them. Instead, I had been allowing my own bias (which came from bad press) to keep me from a fair analysis of the facts.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Whitefield and the Great Awakening conference]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/11/whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference/"/>
	<updated>2014-10-11T16:01:00-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/11/whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/10/whitefield-conference.jpg" alt="Whitefield and the Great Awakening" /><figcaption>Whitefield and the Great Awakening</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I am looking forward to attending the annual conference for the Andrew Fuller Center for Baptist Studies this year on “George Whitefield and the Great Awakening.”</p>
<p>Here is the introduction from the <a href="http://events.sbts.edu/andrewfuller/">conference website</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>George Whitefield was not only the most celebrated preacher of the eighteenth century, but he was also a central figure in the creation of modern Evangelicalism. His emphasis on the new birth, his passion for evangelism, his ability to cross denominational boundaries and build networks of Christians based on the gospel and Reformation convictions were central features in what we know today as Evangelicalism. In this conference celebrating the tercentennial (1714) birth of Whitefield, we will explore these key themes of this remarkable Christian’s life and what they meant for his day and mean for ours.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here are the session titles, taken from the <a href="http://www.andrewfullercenter.org/conference/george-whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-october-21-22-2014/">tentative schedule posted on the AFCBS blog</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Session 1: “The Calvinism of George Whitefield” (Thomas S. Kidd)<br />Session 2: “George Whitefield: Anglican evangelist” (Lee Gatiss)<br />Session 3: “George Whitefield &amp; the Wesleys” (Stephen Nichols)<br />Session 4: “Preaching George Whitefield” (Steve Lawson)<br />Session 5: “The Spirituality of George Whitefield” (Bruce Hindmarsh)<br />Session 6: “Whitefield’s preaching and the politics of Empire” (Jerome Mahaffey)<br />Session 7: “The Legacy of George Whitefield” (David Bebbington)<br />Session 8: “The Hymnody of the Great Awakening” (Esther Crookshank)</p>
</blockquote>
<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/10/tn_9780300181623.jpg" alt="George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father" /><figcaption>George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>As another neat bonus, a few days ago I received my copy of Thomas Kidd’s new biography titled <em>George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father</em> (ISBN 9780300181623). I’m looking forward to digging into this book over the next few days. The hardcover is available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0300181620/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0300181620&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=181623">CBD</a>, and there is also a <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00O56PTU6/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00O56PTU6&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle version</a> available.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Turning Points by Mark Noll]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/09/26/book-review-turning-points-by-mark-noll/"/>
	<updated>2014-09-26T16:19:00-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/09/26/book-review-turning-points-by-mark-noll</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2013/12/noll.jpg" alt="Turning Points by Mark Noll" /><figcaption>Turning Points by Mark Noll</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Noll, Mark A. <em>Turning Points: Decisive Moments in the History of Christianity.</em> 3rd ed. Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2012. ISBN 9780801039966. xii + 356 pages. Includes index.</p>
<p>Available for purchase here:</p>
<ul>
<li>eBook: <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B0085BAEIO/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B0085BAEIO&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon Kindle</a></li>
<li>Paperback: <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=039966">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>This book takes an unusual, and interesting, approach to telling the story of the church by focusing on key turning points throughout the church’s history. Noll describes this approach as “one of the most interesting ways to grasp a general sense of Christian history” (2). The process of identifying these turning points is necessarily subjective, yet he argues that it yields several advantages:</p>
<ul>
<li>“It provides an opportunity to select… and so to bring some order into a massively complicated subject.”</li>
<li>It provides “an opportunity to highlight, to linger over specific moments so as to display the humanity, the complexity, and the uncertainties that constitute the actual history of the church, but that are so often obscured in trying to recount the sweep of centuries.”</li>
<li>It provides “an opportunity to interpret, to state more specifically why certain events, actions, or incidents may have marked an important fork in the road or signaled a new stage in the outworking of Christian history.” (2)</li>
</ul>
<p>The turning points Noll chose can be seen in the table of contents, seen below. <em>[N.B.: The numbers in parentheses for each chapter are dates, not page numbers.]</em></p>
<hr />
<p>Introduction: The Idea of Turning Points and Reasons for Studying the History of Christianity</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Church Pushed Out on Its Own: The Fall of Jerusalem (70)</li>
<li>Realities of Empire: The Council of Nicaea (325)</li>
<li>Doctrine, Politics, and Life in the Word: The Council of Chalcedon (451)</li>
<li>The Monastic Rescue of the Church: Benedict’s <em>Rule</em> (530)</li>
<li>The Culmination of Christendom: The Coronation of Charlemagne (800)</li>
<li>Division between East and West: The Great Schism (1054)</li>
<li>The Beginnings of Protestantism: The Diet of Worms (1521)</li>
<li>A New Europe: The English Act of Supremacy (1534)</li>
<li>Catholic Reform and Worldwide Outreach: The Founding of the Jesuits (1540)</li>
<li>The New Piety: The Conversion of the Wesleys (1738)</li>
<li>Discontents of the Modern West: The French Revolution (1789)</li>
<li>A Faith for All the World: The Edinburgh Missionary Conference (1910)</li>
<li>Mobilizing for the Future: The Second Vatican Council (1962–65) and the Lausanne Congress on World Evangelization (1974)</li>
</ol>
<p>Afterword: The Character of Christianity and the Search for Turning Points</p>
<hr />
<p>Noll emphasizes that “the fourteen turning points singled out for special attention … are by no means the only ones that could have been selected” (3). He explains that the process of selection itself is an important and useful exercise, and notes that “if the book inspires others to think about why the turning points found here are not as important as other possibilities, it will have been a successful book” (4). He then briefly outlines the structure of each chapter, noting that he always begins with “a relatively detailed account of the turning point itself” followed by more theoretical discussions of “why, how, and so what” (4). Additionally, each chapter features a hymn and a prayer from the general time period of the chapter as well as several longer quotations from people involved in the events of the chapter.</p>
<p>After explaining the structure and nature of the book, Noll takes up a larger question: why be concerned about church history at all? Noll offers several reasons why the study of church history is valuable.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>“Studying the history of Christianity provides repeated, concrete demonstration concerning the irreducibly historical character of the Christian faith” (5).</li>
<li>It “provide[s] perspective on the interpretation of Scripture” (6).</li>
<li>“The study of church history is also useful as a laboratory for examining Christian interactions with surrounding culture” (7).</li>
<li>Because “God sustains the church despite the church’s own frequent efforts to betray its Savior and its own high calling, … study of the past can be useful … in shaping proper Christian attitudes” (8).</li>
</ol>
<p>In the introduction, Noll mentions a few of his own convictions which influence his portrayal of the events of church history. He generally prefers the term “history of Christianity” over “church history,” partly because he believes that “‘Christianity’ means something definite with boundaries that are fairly well defined by the major creeds.” Beyond that, Noll writes with “evangelical Protestant convictions” that “lead [him] to think that revitalized forms of Reformation faith are the truest and best forms of Christianity” (9–10). Noll qualifies this belief, however, with the observation that “historical study has convinced me that confessional Protestants have sometimes honored the ideals of the Reformation more in words than in reality. Historical study also shows that believers in other Christian traditions regularly display Christlike virtues and practice humble dependence upon God’s grace more than my confessional Protestant convictions tell me they should.” As a result, he has “tried to write with as much respect as possible for the widely diverse forms of Christianity that have been practiced with integrity, and continue to be practiced with integrity, in all parts of the Christian church” (10).</p>
<p>Of course, Noll’s statements regarding Catholicism reflect his perspective as an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evangelicals_and_Catholics_Together#Endorsed_By">endorser of <em>Evangelicals and Catholics Together</em> in 1994</a>. I think it is useful to read authors from outside my own tradition, but that does not obviate the need to read with discernment.</p>
<p>Noll’s book is helpful for a number of different reasons.</p>
<ul>
<li>By approaching the history of Christianity from the vantage point of key turning points, he provides an interesting and unusual perspective. This also enables the chapters to stand on their own while still making sense to a reader who reads the book through from beginning to end.</li>
<li>Noll’s writing style is simultaneously lucid and dense. He is capable of drawing complex connections between seemingly unrelated events, yet throughout the process his ideas remain incredibly clear. My students all said that they enjoyed his writing, but that he always forced them to think carefully.</li>
<li><p>Over the course of the book, he develops several key ideas into recurring themes. One example appears in Chapter 1, where he argues that the fall of Jerusalem created a new problem for the Christian church. Suddenly severed from any connection to its Jewish roots, the church was forced to emerge as an independent entity while maintaining a connection to its apostolic roots. The need to establish <em>apostolicity</em> could be resolved in three different ways: by appealing to the authority of the New Testament canon, by appealing to the authority of the emerging episcopacy, or by appealing to the authority of the apostolic creeds. What is interesting about these three distinct sources of stability is that Protestants, Roman Catholics, and the Orthodox each tend to place more emphasis on one of those three, as displayed in the chart below:</p>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 25%" />
<col style="width: 30%" />
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Tradition</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Stabilizing Element</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Protestants</p></td>
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Canon</p></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Roman Catholics</p></td>
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Episcopacy</p></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Orthodox</p></td>
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Creed</p></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>As the history of the church progresses through time, Noll quite effectively shows how these three contrasting sources of authority shape future conflicts within the church.</p>
<p>Another example of a recurring theme throughout the book is the concept of <em>Christendom,</em> the idea which began to develop in the post-Roman European world that Christ’s kingdom extended to a specific geographical location (Europe), and that thus church and state ought to be deeply entwined. The idea of Christendom appears to climax in the coronation of Charlemagne, and much of the spiritual and political energy of the Medieval period is wrapped up in preserving that (un)holy (un)Roman (un)Empire.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Although each chapter is interesting and carefully researched, it does become evident that some chapters play more to Noll’s strengths than others. From time to time, he indicates in a footnote that he is depending upon another secondary source for much of his material in a chapter. In other chapters where the subject material is within an area where he has done extensive research, he writes with considerably more freedom as he draws upon his own extensive knowledge. An example of one of his stronger chapters is chapter 10 on the Evangelical Revival under the Wesleys (his name appears twice in the “Further Reading” section at the end of the chapter), and an example of one of his weaker chapters is chapter 9 on the Jesuits. Still, his skills as a researcher shine throughout, and there is a remarkable uniformity of quality throughout.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Speaking in BC and NC this summer]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/06/03/speaking-in-bc-and-nc-this-summer/"/>
	<updated>2014-06-03T11:37:00-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/06/03/speaking-in-bc-and-nc-this-summer</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This summer I will be in British Columbia and North Carolina to speak. I will be at <a href="http://gbcvic.org/">Grace Baptist Church of Victoria</a> July 6–12. I’ll speak in the church services that Sunday, and then during the week I’ll be offering my Th105 Church History Survey course as a block class throughout the week. Then, on July 27, I’ll be at <a href="http://www.faithbaptistlinville.org/">Faith Baptist Church (Linville, NC)</a> during the Sunday services. I’ll be giving three sessions on the area of Baptist history.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Man's Wisdom vs. God's Wisdom]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/05/25/mans-wisdom-vs-gods-wisdom/"/>
	<updated>2014-05-25T08:09:00-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/05/25/mans-wisdom-vs-gods-wisdom</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every now and then, you hear somebody preach a sermon that really sticks in your memory. For me, this happened when I heard <a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/pr103-2012/media/sermon-mans-wisdom-vs-gods-wisdom/">this sermon</a> by Brent Cook in chapel at Bob Jones University. The message takes 1 Cor. 1:18 as its foundational text:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For the message of the cross is foolishness to those who are perishing, but to us who are being saved it is the power of God. (1 Corinthians 1:18 NKJ)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I replayed this sermon for my students in my class on evangelism a year later (the link above goes to the website for that course), and I’ve listened to this message many times since. It came to mind again today as I was studying 2 Cor. 2:12–3:18.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Ryle on Preaching Simply]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/05/17/ryle-on-preaching-simply/"/>
	<updated>2014-05-17T22:13:00-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/05/17/ryle-on-preaching-simply</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/05/ryle.jpg" title="J. C. Ryle" alt="J. C. Ryle" /><figcaption>J. C. Ryle</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I just read a little booklet by J. C. Ryle. Titled <em>Simplicity in Preaching: A Few Short Hints on a Great Subject</em>, the book contains a lecture Ryle delivered in 1882 and spans 48 tiny pages (each page includes only a couple paragraphs). I suspect that the entire thing would work today as a lengthy blog post.</p>
<p>Much of what Ryle says is helpful, though some of it reflects the prevailing ideas of his times and is less useful now (e.g., his ambivalence towards the use of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linguistic_purism_in_English">“Saxon words” in English</a>). Though I recommend you <a href="http://books.google.ca/books/about/Simplicity_in_preaching_a_few_short_hint.html?id=MgkDAAAAQAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y">read the whole thing</a>, here are five directives Ryle gives to those who would attain simplicity in preaching:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Have a clear knowledge of what you are going to preach.</li>
<li>Use simple words.</li>
<li>Seek to acquire a simple style of composition, with short sentences and as few colons and semi-colons as possible.</li>
<li>Aim at directness.</li>
<li>Make abundant use of illustration and anecdote.</li>
</ol>
<p>HT: <a href="https://twitter.com/steveweaver/status/467830530336382977">Steve Weaver</a><br />Image credit: By Kowalker [CC-BY-SA-3.0 (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0)], via <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:J_C_Ryle.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Timeline of Old Testament Israel]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/04/05/timeline-of-old-testament-israel/"/>
	<updated>2014-04-05T17:13:00-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/04/05/timeline-of-old-testament-israel</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I am making available a project that I’ve only recently begun. This project had its genesis a few years back when I created a <a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/Isaiah-Visualizations/">timeline of events relevant to the Old Testament book of Isaiah</a>.</p>
<p>Last week, I took that work and expanded it into something I’ve had in mind for a while—a more comprehensive <a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/OT-Timeline/">timeline of the history of Israel</a>. Right now, this only covers Old Testament Israel from the reign of Saul to the post-exilic period, and the details are sparse in some periods and heavy in others (esp. during the period of Isaiah’s life). There are many more things I’d like to do with this later, but I thought I’d make what I have so far available, especially since it’s relevant to the <a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/ex315-2014/">class I’m teaching right now</a> on the Old Testament Historical Books.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Block class on John's Epistles]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/03/10/block-class-on-johns-epistles/"/>
	<updated>2014-03-10T10:00:00-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/03/10/block-class-on-johns-epistles</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ll be teaching a block class on John’s letters this coming April 28–May 3. I thought I’d share the book for this class (as well as some general information) below. More details (including the syllabus and assignment list) will be forthcoming soon on the <a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/ex315-2014/">course website</a>.</p>
<p><em>Description:</em> An exposition of 1, 2, and 3 John, with an emphasis on John’s theology.</p>
<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/03/tn_9780802825186.jpg" alt="The Epistles of John" /><figcaption>The Epistles of John</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><em>Textbook:</em> Marshall, I. Howard. <em>The Epistles of John.</em> New International Commentary on the New Testament. Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 2001. ISBN 9780802825186.</p>
<p>Available for purchase here:</p>
<ul>
<li>eBook: <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B0028Y4AYS/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B0028Y4AYS&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon Kindle</a><br /> (<em>Note:</em> I wouldn’t recommend getting a technical commentary like this on Kindle, but this is a matter of preference.)</li>
<li>Hardcover:
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0802825184/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0802825184&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=2189">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Readings in Baptist History: Four Centuries of Selected Documents by Joe Early]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/02/12/book-review-readings-in-baptist-history-four-centuries-of-selected-documents-by-joe-early/"/>
	<updated>2014-02-12T13:05:00-07:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/02/12/book-review-readings-in-baptist-history-four-centuries-of-selected-documents-by-joe-early</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/02/early.jpg" alt="Readings in Baptist History by Joe Early" /><figcaption>Readings in Baptist History by Joe Early</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Early, Joseph. <em>Readings in Baptist History: Four Centuries of Selected Documents.</em> Nashville, TN: B&amp;H Academic, 2008. ISBN 9780805446746. 288 pages.</p>
<p>Available for purchase from:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=446746">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0805446745/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0805446745&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca (Canada)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0805446745/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0805446745&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20">Amazon.com (USA)</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>By necessity, the study of history requires the perusal of historic texts. By devoting attention to primary sources, the student learns from the perspective of eyewitnesses and participants. Sometimes reading primary sources uncovers the student’s own bias; at other times it presents the biases of the original actors in their own context. In studying any historical period or genre, beginning students oftentimes ignore important primary sources, not necessarily from lack of interest, but because those texts are scattered in various locations. A common remedy for this problem is a sourcebook, a published edition of key primary sources on a given topic. Joseph Early’s <em>Readings in Baptist History</em> provides an up-to-date sourcebook of key Baptist texts in one affordable volume.</p>
<p>This work fills a largely overlooked niche in the literature on Baptist history. In his preface, Early observes that although several books on Baptist history have appeared since H. Leon McBeth’s <em>Baptist Heritage: Four Centuries of Baptist Witness</em> in 1987, no new sourcebook has been produced since the 1990 release of McBeth’s companion volume, <em>A Sourcebook for Baptist Heritage.</em> In this work, Early adds newer documents while also including “seminal older documents” (v) to provide a comprehensive update.</p>
<p>In selecting texts for inclusion, Early seeks “to provide as broad a scope and be as inclusive as possible” (vi). As a result, representative texts from a variety of Baptist traditions appear within the collection, including “British Baptists, Black Baptists, American Baptists, Southern Baptists, Russian Baptists, Landmark Baptists, and Fundamental Baptists” (vi). Of course, selecting key texts to include means that some texts must be excluded, and Early notes that his selections were limited by word count and the interests of his intended audience of “students of Baptist history” (vi).</p>
<p>The selections in the book are organized chronologically, beginning with texts from the exiled English General Baptists led by John Smyth and Thomas Helwys in 1609. The book exhibits a generally even distribution of texts over the course of Baptist history, with seven chapters from the seventeenth century, eight from the eighteenth century, twelve from the nineteenth century, and fourteen from the twentieth century. A complete chapter listing is included below this review for those interested in the details.</p>
<p>One editorial decision is unfortunate, though based on admirable motives. In the interest of appealing to a broad readership, there are no editorial introductions to the various texts included in the work. Early indicates that he chose not to include comments on individual texts so that he would not “color the interpretation of the documents” (vi). Unfortunately, this means that students sometimes struggle to understand the significance and place of the documents within the broader context of Baptist history.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most significant contribution of the book is that it includes documents relevant to the theological controversy within the Southern Baptist Convention. In the chapter that includes the Baptist Faith and Message, the three different versions (1925, 1963, 2000) are presented in three parallel columns for easy comparison.</p>
<p>My own students reacted to the book quite positively, although at first they seemed unexcited by the prospect of reading a collection of source texts. As their background knowledge of the Baptist story developed over the semester, they became more interested in the readings. By the end of the semester, some of my students were saying that they enjoyed reading Early even more than their other textbook.</p>
<p>For a bibliography of supplemental readings, see <a href="http://www.baptisttheology.org/book-reviews/readings-in-baptist-history">the review by Jason G. Duesing of Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
<!-- more -->
<hr />
<p><em>List of Chapters</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Character of the Beast, 1609</li>
<li>Letter to Sir William Hammerton, 1609</li>
<li>A Declaration of Faith of English People Remaining in Amsterdam in Holland, 1611</li>
<li>A Short Declaration of the Mystery of Iniquity, 1612</li>
<li>The Beginnings of the Particular Baptists and the Birth of Immersion, 1633</li>
<li>The Bloudy Tennent of Persecution, 1644</li>
<li>The Whipping of Obadiah Holmes, 1651</li>
<li>The Power of the Association, 1749</li>
<li>The Birth of the Charleston Association, 1751</li>
<li>Birth of the Sandy Creek Baptist Association, 1758</li>
<li>A Body of Doctrinal and Practical Divinity, 1769</li>
<li>An Appeal to the Public for Religious Liberty, 1773</li>
<li>Black Baptists</li>
<li>The Rights of Conscience Inalienable, 1791</li>
<li>An Enquiry, 1792</li>
<li>The “Wall of Separation”</li>
<li>Formation of the English Baptist Union, 1813</li>
<li>Address at the Formation of the Triennial Convention, 1814</li>
<li>Treatise on Slavery, 1822</li>
<li>Primitivism and the Antimission Movement</li>
<li>Report and Warning about Campbellism, 1830</li>
<li>The Georgia Test Case and the Alabama Resolutions</li>
<li>Southern and Northern Perspectives on the 1845 Schism</li>
<li>Address Explaining Why the Southern Baptist Convention was Organized, 1845</li>
<li>Old Landmarkism: What is It?</li>
<li>A Letter from China</li>
<li>Another Word Concerning the Down-Grade</li>
<li>The Baptist World Alliance</li>
<li>The Kingdom of God, 1917</li>
<li>Baptists and Religious Liberty, 1920</li>
<li>The Impact of J. Frank Norris on Baptist Life</li>
<li>The Cooperative Program, 1924</li>
<li>The Trail of Blood, 1931</li>
<li>The Baptist Way, 1945</li>
<li>Russian Baptist History from 1929 to 1963, 1967</li>
<li>Origins of the Conservative Resurgence</li>
<li>The Resurgence of Calvinism</li>
<li>Peace Committee Report, 1987</li>
<li>Doctrinal Statement of the Baptist Missionary Association of America, 1989</li>
<li>The Cooperative Baptist Fellowship</li>
<li>The Baptist Faith and Message, 1925, 1963, 2000</li>
</ol>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Baptist Ways: A History by Bill Leonard]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/01/16/book-review-baptist-ways-a-history-by-bill-leonard/"/>
	<updated>2014-01-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/01/16/book-review-baptist-ways-a-history-by-bill-leonard</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/01/leonard.jpg" alt="Baptist Ways by Bill Leonard" /><figcaption>Baptist Ways by Bill Leonard</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Leonard, Bill J. <em>Baptist Ways: A History.</em> Valley Forge, PA: Judson Press, 2003. ISBN 9780817012311. xiv + 464 pages.</p>
<p>Available for purchase from:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=012311">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0817012311/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0817012311&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca (Canada)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0817012311/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0817012311&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20">Amazon.com (USA)</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>Conceived as a replacement for Robert Torbet’s well-known text, <em>A History of the Baptists</em>, this book attempts to survey the worldwide history of Baptists from their origins in seventeeth-century England. Leonard states his thesis clearly in the opening paragraph of his preface:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The thesis of this book is relatively simple. It suggests that amid certain distinctives, Baptist identity is configured in a variety of ways by groups, subgroups, and individuals who claim the Baptist name. This identity extends across a theological spectrum from Arminian to Calvinist, from conservative to liberal, from open to closed communionist, and from denominationalist to independent.” (xi)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This thesis allows Leonard to include a broad survey of individuals and groups, including giving significant attention to the role of women and minorities in the history of the Baptists. One interesting feature is regular description of Baptist hymnody and worship. Throughout the work, Leonard draws primarily from secondary sources, although the notes (which are placed as endnotes after each chapter) indicate a measured use of primary sources.</p>
<p>The book alternates between chronological and geographical perspectives. Chapter 1 provides a standard introduction to the study of Baptist history, surveying common doctrinal distinctives and contrasting the three views of Baptist origins. Chapters 2–9 proceed chronologically, telling the story of English and American Baptists from their obscure seventeenth-century beginnings to national prominence during the nineteenth-century. Chapters 10–14 survey the Baptist movement elsewhere, giving the book a global scope. For instance, chapter 10 provides a concise summary of Baptists in Canada (227–244), followed by brief sections on Baptist efforts in various Latin American countries. These chapters will be of most interest to readers outside the United States, but are important for all readers to provide a full understanding of the various kinds of Baptists to be found throughout the world. Chapters 15 and 16 resume the story of Baptists in the West during the twentieth century.</p>
<p><em>Chapters</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Baptist Ways: Defining a People</li>
<li>Baptist Beginnings: The Historical Context</li>
<li>English Baptists: The Seventeenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: Beginnings</li>
<li>English Baptists: The Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: The Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in Britain: The Nineteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: 1800-1845</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: 1845-1900</li>
<li>Baptists in the Americas and the Caribbean</li>
<li>African American Baptists</li>
<li>Baptists in Greater Britain</li>
<li>Baptists in Europe</li>
<li>Baptists in Africa and Asia</li>
<li>Baptists in the British Isles and Europe: The Twentieth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: The Twentieth Century</li>
</ol>
<!-- Omit following paragraph... not sure I have the right examples, although I know I felt this way at various points in the book. Too bad I didn't mark it. -->
<!-- Due to the broad scope of the book, Leonard frequently mentions names and events without remarking on their significance. Examples of this include his mention of Benoi Stinson (211--212) and James Manning (231). Without  -->
<p>Predictably, the book reflects the denominational affiliation of its publisher, Judson Press. As the <a href="http://www.judsonpress.com/home_about_us.cfm">publishing arm of the American Baptist Churches USA</a>, Judson Press represents a particular constituency of Baptists. The book puts some emphasis on this strain of Baptist identity, tracing the development of the ABCUSA out of the Northern Baptist Convention in some detail in chapter 16.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the book omits or downplays some important events in Southern Baptist history. For instance, the extensive controversy over the modernism of Crawford H. Toy receives no treatment. Toy, though he was professor at The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary from 1869–1879, is only mentioned as a missionary appointee to Japan who “never went because the [Foreign Mission Board] delayed all appointments in anticipation of the Civil War and related economic difficulties” (353). The dates of his professorship at Southern appear only in an otherwise unremarkable parenthesis, and there is no mention of his broken engagement to missionary Lottie Moon. As <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/30149574">other reviewers</a> <a href="http://www.baptisttheology.org/book-reviews/baptist-ways-a-history/">have noted</a>, the Conservative Resurgence in the SBC also receives scant coverage, appearing only in summary on pages 414–415.</p>
<p>Occasionally, the book suggests that an emphasis on biblical literalism results in erratic or erroneous conclusions. An early example of this pattern occurs in the treatment of John Smyth, the early sixteenth-century Baptist. Smyth was certainly unstable, following a spiritual trajectory that parallels that of Roger Williams in America. Smyth began as an Anglican until he adopted Separatist views. Later, he founded the General Baptists along with Thomas Helwys by baptizing himself and then his own followers. This self-baptism brought criticism, and eventually Smyth repudiated his own baptism and sought admission into a nearby Mennonite sect. The book attributes Smyth’s restlessness to his commitment to the Bible: “His biblicism took him through many Protestant communities in a search for the fullest revelation available” (25). Smyth was undoubtedly a biblicist, but there are other explanations for his repudiation of his self-baptism. On occasion, the book suggests that biblicism leads to other negative results, which will disappoint conservative readers.</p>
<p>Other reviews have been mixed in their final appraisal of Leonard’s text, despite the unanimous acknowledgement that producing a one-volume Baptist history is a difficult task. As a potential course textbook, the work suffers from a lack of visual aids (a deficiency that equally applies to the competing volumes by Torbet and McBeth). Other complaints include the slightly negative treatment of more conservative Baptist traditions and the deliberately international focus of chapters 10–16. On the other hand, these two complaints illustrate and, to some degree, substantiate Leonard’s thesis that Baptists are a broadly differentiated sect. As a potential textbook for a course on Baptist history, I find Leonard’s text to be useful despite these perceived weaknesses. This is especially true for me as I teach the history of the Baptists outside of the United States of America. Although Leonard’s book should not be the only volume that students of the Baptists consult, I am convinced that it is a worthy member of the body of literature on the topic.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Textbooks for my Courses Next Semester]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/12/24/textbooks-for-my-courses-next-semester/"/>
	<updated>2013-12-24T14:53:00-07:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/12/24/textbooks-for-my-courses-next-semester</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This coming semester I’ll be teaching two courses, Church History Survey and Historical Books. I thought I’d post a few links here for anyone who might be planning to take one of these classes.</p>
<h2 id="th105-church-history-survey">Th105 Church History Survey</h2>
<p><a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/th105-2014/">Course website</a></p>
<p><em>Description:</em> Surveys the people, places and dates most important in understanding how the Holy Spirit has been saving, sanctifying and organizing people for the past two millennia.</p>
<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2013/12/noll.jpg" alt="Turning Points" /><figcaption>Turning Points</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><em>Textbook:</em> Noll, Mark A. <em>Turning Points: Decisive Moments in the History of Christianity.</em> 3rd ed. Baker Academic, 2012. ISBN 9780801039966.</p>
<p>Available for purchase here:</p>
<ul>
<li>eBook: <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B0085BAEIO/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B0085BAEIO&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon Kindle</a></li>
<li>Paperback: <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=039966">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="su401-historical-books">Su401 Historical Books</h2>
<p><a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/su401-2014/">Course website</a></p>
<p><em>Description:</em> Overviews Joshua through Esther, emphasizing chronology and historical background. Highlights the introduction to each book (date of composition, author, occasion &amp; purpose, and recipients) and themes. Discusses contemporary application.</p>
<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2013/12/hamilton.jpg" alt="Handbook on the Historical Books" /><figcaption>Handbook on the Historical Books</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Hamilton, Victor P. <em>Handbook on the Historical Books: Joshua, Judges, Ruth, Samuel, Kings, Chronicles, Ezra-Nehemiah, Esther.</em> Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 2008. ISBN 9780801036149.</p>
<p>Available for purchase here:</p>
<ul>
<li>ebook: <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00CFKX6I6/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00CFKX6I6&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon Kindle</a></li>
<li>Paperback: <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=036149">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Student Work Showcase: Baptist History Timeline]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/12/06/student-work-showcase-baptist-history-timeline/"/>
	<updated>2013-12-06T11:08:00-07:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/12/06/student-work-showcase-baptist-history-timeline</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/Baptist-History/"><img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2013/11/timeline.png" alt="Baptist History Timeline project" /></a></p>
<p>This semester, students in my <a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/th106-2013/">Baptist History class</a> were responsible for a <a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/th106-2013/project/">group project</a> to construct an <a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/Baptist-History/">online timeline</a> of key events in the history of the Baptist movement. It has been rather interesting to watch this project develop as the students submitted events and presented their findings to the class. Since my students submitted their final entries this week, I thought I’d share their work, write down my observations on the project as a classroom assignment, and note some ideas I’ve had for ways to use this in the future.</p>
<!-- more -->
<h2 id="thoughts-on-educational-value">Thoughts on Educational Value</h2>
<p>As an assignment, I found that this was a useful project in several ways.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>It created interest in the course by allowing students to explore areas of interest. Some of my students said that they didn’t like the class at first, but as a result of the project it was now one of their favorite classes.</li>
<li>It encouraged my students to read widely from the literature.</li>
<li>The atomistic nature of the assignment (30 separate timeline entries submitted in smaller assignments over the semester) was less intimidating than a 10-20 page paper on a single topic. This makes it an interesting project for a survey class, as it allows students with no prior knowledge or interest to expand their knowledge in any direction they choose.</li>
<li>It forced my beginning history students to grapple with questions of significance as they analyzed historical events. In selecting events for their timeline contributions, students had to decide whether an event was truly significant for the grand story of the Baptists throughout history. Sometimes they made good choices and sometimes they didn’t, but the exercise itself helped to introduce them to the basics of selecting and evaluating evidence.</li>
</ol>
<p>Of course, there are some inherent weaknesses too.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Because it focuses on dates and data, the project doesn’t require the construction of a coherent argument or narrative. My goal was to supplement this deficiency through reading assignments and lectures, and to some extent student performance on assessments suggests that this actually worked.</li>
<li>Because students come to the project with limited knowledge, their choices tend to reflect inherent prejudices and/or emphases from class lectures.</li>
<li>Because students were required to submit a specific quota of events, they did not always select truly significant events. I tried to reflect that in my marks for their assignments, but overall I’m happy with the results of their work.</li>
<li>Because it emphasizes finding separate events, it tends to result in superficial knowledge rather than deep comprehension.</li>
</ol>
<p>There are probably other observations I could make on the effect of this assignment, but this is enough for now. In summary, I thought it was a worthwhile project and a useful student assignment which I’ll repeat in future offerings of this class.</p>
<h2 id="ideas-for-future-implementation">Ideas for Future Implementation</h2>
<p>This sort of project is something I’ve done by myself a few times before. Examples of my own efforts this way can be found on my <a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/projects/">Projects page</a>. As I review the events which my students chose for their contributions, there are a number of things I would probably do differently.</p>
<p>I have plenty of ideas for things that I could do with this project at some later date. These ideas roughly break down into three areas: 1) pedagogy, 2) content and 3) technical.</p>
<h3 id="pedagogy">Pedagogy</h3>
<p>One oversight in my <a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/th106-2013/project/">project definition</a> was any reference to grammar, spelling, and capitalization. I shouldn’t need to worry about this at this level, but the simple reality is that my students tend to struggle with these things. This should factor into their marks, but it didn’t for this class because my expectations were too idealistic.</p>
<h3 id="content">Content</h3>
<p>At some point, I’d like to take my students’ contributions, edit them, and put them into a fresh dataset that represents my own perspective on the history of Baptists. If I ever do this, I will keep the appropriate “Contributor” attribute in the dataset to acknowledge the original work of my students. In many ways, their submissions exhibit a level of passion that my own timeline projects have never had.</p>
<p>If I ever do that, here are some things I would change:</p>
<ul>
<li>I’d place less focus on individuals and organizations and more focus on concrete events. Although many of the individuals/organizations my students selected are important, I’m not sure that representing the duration of some of these peoples’ lives is truly significant for the full story of the Baptists. Some individuals truly were significant over the course of their life, such as Charles Spurgeon and William Carey. Others, though, are perhaps better remembered for a few accomplishments than for a lifetime of significant efforts, such as perhaps Benoi Stinson or Sarah Cummings.</li>
<li>I’d reorganize the events under a more uniform set of categories that are defined in terms of specific chronological periods. At the beginning, I defined only three simple categories for my students: “English Particular Baptists,” “English General Baptists,” and “Baptists in America.” These categories are really only useful for telling the story of Baptists from their founding in the 1600s until around the end of the 18th century. After that, those categories become rather clunky. For instance, “Baptists in America” would probably make more sense if I changed it to “Baptists in America before 1845.” After 1845, I’d need to create separate categories for Northern and Southern Baptists, as well as other groups of Baptists that developed after that time.</li>
<li>I’d edit my student entries to only include the most significant entries. In other words, in producing my own dataset based on their contributions, I’d filter out the submissions that where significance is questionable. I’d still retain their work in a data file that includes all the entries made by that particular class, but not all of those entries would make it into my edited version of the dataset.</li>
<li>I’d also supplement student contributions to correct for lacunae. My students did some admirable work on this project, and in many cases identified truly significant events to display. However, they still missed a few truly significant things, either due to a lack of knowledge or interest. For instance, one of my students included several of Adoniram Judson’s wives, but not one of my students thought to create an entry for Adoniram Judson himself.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="technical">Technical</h3>
<p>This project depends on code (specifically, the <a href="http://simile-widgets.org/">Simile Exhibit Timeline plugin</a>). As a result, there are always technical things that need maintenance, as well as technical opportunities that could be explored. Someday, here are some things that I’d love to get done to make this sort of project more useful.</p>
<ul>
<li>Change the lens design to include links to copies of the original text of a document when available in a similar way to the wikipedia links.</li>
<li>Implement multiple datasets so the same code can be reused for each class where I give this as an assignment.</li>
<li>Upgrade the timeline code to take advantage of improvements in Simile Exhibit 3.0 (or one of the newer implementations that can be found in the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/simile-widgets">SIMILE Widgets Google Group</a>). Apparently there are <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/4700419/alternative-to-simile-timeline-for-timeline-visualization">other projects out there that do similar things</a> (some of which may even work better), but I’m too heavily invested in the Simile Exhibit framework to be interested in switching to an alternate platform right now.</li>
<li>Develop a better system for submitting entries that supports image upload and supports additional file formats (SVG was a problem). I’m not completely sure how I would set this up. Ultimately, I’d probably need to set up access to Amazon S3 storage, but there’s no way to easily incorporate that into my current system where students submit entries via a Google Spreadsheets form and can immediately see the results on the timeline itself.</li>
<li>Implement geo-code support within the timeline dataset, and then implement functionality to switch between timeline view and map view. Because geo-code data requires advanced technical skills to generate, this is not something I would require students to submit but would be nice to have in edited versions of the dataset.</li>
</ul>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Historical roots of local-church-onlyism]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/11/05/historical-roots-of-local-church-onlyism/"/>
	<updated>2013-11-05T13:36:00-07:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/11/05/historical-roots-of-local-church-onlyism</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’d like to add a few comments on an interesting debate over at my Dad’s blog about the New Testament’s use of the term translated “church” (<em>ekklesia</em>).</p>
<ul>
<li>In <a href="http://oxgoad.ca/2013/10/22/ekklesia/">one post</a>, he argues that the biblical usage of the term “church” suggests that there is such a thing as the “universal church,” defined as “a universal body of believers that includes all believers from all ages in one spiritual union, the church.”</li>
<li>In a <a href="http://oxgoad.ca/2013/10/27/ekklesia-part-2/">followup</a>, he goes further, demonstrating from biblical texts that the word is also used for what we call the “visible church,” inclusive of the sum total of professing believers on earth.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="why-does-this-matter">Why does this matter?</h2>
<p>Suggesting that the word “church” can mean anything other than a “local church” can get you into trouble with some Baptists, and so an interesting discussion broke out in the comments on both posts. In the comments, my Dad asks one question for his local-church-only interlocutors: <strong>“Why is the idea of local church only so important? Or, to put it another way, why is the idea of the universal church dangerous?”</strong></p>
<h2 id="ideas-and-consequences">Ideas and Consequences</h2>
<p>I’d like to suggest one reason why local-church-only advocates cannot concede the existence of the universal church. (Of course, doing so requires that they ignore the plain reading of texts such as Ephesians 1:22–23, but for the exegesis I refer you again to <a href="http://oxgoad.ca/2013/10/22/ekklesia/">the original post</a>.) <!-- more --> The idea that the term “church” can only refer to a local assembly is simply a necessary corollary of Landmarkist theology. Landmarkism depends on an uninterrupted succession of local assemblies to support the theory that the “true church” comprises the Baptist tradition throughout the ages. This (widely discredited) view of history is known as <a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/th106-2013/lectures/lecture-1-theories-of-baptist-origins/">Baptist successionism</a>.</p>
<p>If a Landmarkist allows for a universal aspect to the church, he implies that genuine believers might be found outside of the supposed succession of local churches (the “Baptists”) but within the scope of Christendom (including medieval Catholics).</p>
<p>Because the Landmarkist is predisposed to avoid that conclusion, he must go to great lengths to justify a local-only view of the church. Seen in this light, the local-only view becomes nothing more than part of an artificial perimeter around the Landmarkist theory.</p>
<h2 id="historical-evidence">Historical Evidence</h2>
<p>If the explanation above is correct, we would expect to find the idea that the local-church-only idea in the writings of the early Landmarkists. Today, I ran across some evidence that confirms that early Landmarkists indeed believed that the Bible does not allow for a universal or invisible church.</p>
<figure>
<img src="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/th106-2013/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2013/08/220px-JamesRobinsonGraves.jpg" title="J. R. Graves" alt="J. R. Graves" /><figcaption>J. R. Graves</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>J. R. Graves was not the first to hold Landmarkism, but he was certainly one its most vociferous early proponents. Through his influence, successionist historiography and Landmark ecclesiology became a significant force within American Baptist circles.</p>
<p>In Leon McBeth’s history of the Baptist movement, he notes that Graves believed the church to be “a single congregation, complete in itself, independent of all other bodies, civil or religious, … amenable only to Christ.”<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a> He thought that the “invisible church” was nothing more than “invisible nonsense.” In a more extended quote, Graves argues that</p>
<blockquote>
<p>the only church that is revealed to us is a visible church, and the only church with which we have anything to do, or in connection with which we have any duties to perform, is a visible body…. Christ never set up but one kingdom; and if this is visible, he has no invisible kingdom or church, and such a thing has no real existence in heaven or earth. It is only an invention to bolster up erroneous theories of ecclesiology.<a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"><sup>2</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="evaluation">Evaluation</h2>
<p>In evaluating Graves’ statements, this quote from Sidney Ahlstrom is telling.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At the heart of Graves’s argument was a doctrine of the Kingdom which allowed a syllogism to do the work of historical research: the Kingdom has prevailed; the Kingdom must always have included true churches; Baptist churches are the only true churches; therefore, Baptist churches have always existed.<a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"><sup>3</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>As an historical theory, successionism is bankrupt because it is based on an absence of evidence. Likewise, the view that the New Testament only speaks of the local church requires us to ignore clear biblical evidence. It seems to me that the only reason to hold this view is to support the scaffold for the rest of Landmark theology.</p>
<section class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>J. R. Graves quoted in Leon McBeth, <em>The Baptist Heritage</em> (Nashville, TN: Broadman Press, 1987), 450–451.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Ibid., 451.<a href="#fnref2">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Sydney E. Ahlstrom, <em>A Religious History of the American People</em> (New Haven, Conn.: Yale Univ. Press, 1972), 723.<a href="#fnref3">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[Hoehner on Ephesians 4:4-6]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/11/03/hoehner-on-ephesians-4-4-6/"/>
	<updated>2013-11-03T14:34:00-07:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/11/03/hoehner-on-ephesians-4-4-6</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0801026148/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=330641&amp;creativeASIN=0801026148&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20"><img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2013/11/hoehner.jpg" alt="Hoehner on Ephesians" /></a></p>
<p>Today in my Adult Bible study class at <a href="http://www.meadowlandsbaptist.ca/">Meadowlands Baptist Church</a> we discussed these verses in Ephesians 4:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><sup>NKJ</sup> <strong>Ephesians 4:4-6</strong> There is one body and one Spirit, just as you were called in one hope of your calling; <sup>5</sup> one Lord, one faith, one baptism; <sup>6</sup> one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I found <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0801026148/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=330641&amp;creativeASIN=0801026148&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Hoehner</a> to be helpful in unpacking Paul’s meaning in these verses, so I decided to share his comments on these verses.</p>
<!-- more -->
<blockquote>
<p><strong>4:4.</strong> The sevenfold use of “one” (εἷς, μία, ἕν) emphasizes unity.</p>
<p>First, there is one body (ἓν σῶμα), which refers to the universal church already discussed (1:23; 2:16; 3:5–6). … it is not that Gentiles become Jews, as in the OT, nor Jews become Gentiles, but that unbelieving Jews and Gentiles become one body of believers when they place their faith in the work of Christ at Calvary. They are no longer two entities but one.</p>
<p>Second, there is the one Spirit (ἓν πνεῦμα) referring to the Holy Spirit. …</p>
<p>Third, there is one hope.With this clause Paul breaks from the pattern of verses 4a and 5–6 and refers back to the call mentioned in verse 1. He does this in order to give a conceptual framework on which the rest of the exhortation is based. … The noun ἐλπίς, “hope,” was discussed in 1:18 and was defined as eager expectation of the outworking of God’s plan. The hope presented in Ephesians is the reality that all things will be headed up in Christ (1:9) and though the believers are presently seated with Christ, in the future they will be displayed in heaven as trophies of his grace (2:7). Further, they have been brought near to God, united into one body in Christ and reconciled to God (2:11–3:13). Before this they were without hope and without God in the world (2:12). Hence, there is the element of objective hope which is laid up for the believers (cf. Col 1:5; Rom 8:24), and this serves as the basis of the subjective hope. Hope for believers is not the world’s “hope so” but the absolute certainty that God will deliver what he has promised.</p>
<p>In conclusion, then, the elements of unity are portrayed in the one body, the one Spirit, and the one hope of their calling. The third person of the Trinity is the unifier in this verse.</p>
<p><strong>4:5.</strong> Fourth, there is one Lord. In the previous verse the third person of the Trinity was discussed, Paul now considers the second person, Christ. The word κύριος logically refers to Christ since Paul has just discussed the Holy Spirit in verse 4 and will discuss the Father in the next verse. Christ is the “one Lord” who provided redemption (1:7), hope (1:12), and headship over the church (1:22–23).</p>
<p>Fifth, there is one faith. The “one faith” does not have reference to an objective faith, the body of truth believed by Christians … as some propose, but rather to the subjective faith which is exercised by all Christians in Christ their Lord (cf. Col 2:7). … In the first chapter of this book, Paul mentions that the Ephesians had expressed their faith when they heard the message (1:13) and that their faith in the Lord Jesus was widely known (1:15). Thus, it is the one faith in the one Lord.</p>
<p>Sixth, there is one baptism. This phrase has caused some debate. There are two major views and a third should be considered. First, most commentators think it has reference to water baptism. … Second, some consider it to be a reference to the Spirit’s baptism. … A third option that needs to be considered is that it refers metaphorically to the believer’s baptism into Christ’s death, speaking of the believer’s union with Christ in his death and resurrection. … This same concept is seen in other NT passages (Rom 6:1–11; Gal. 3:27; Col 2:12). Furthermore, it fits well with the context, for the believer’s baptism into Christ signifies union with Christ (Rom 6:5) and it occurs at the time of conversion (Rom 6:2–4). This inward reality is all too often missed. It serves as the basis of the outward ritual. Hence, the “one baptism” most likely refers to the internal reality of having been baptized into (identified with) the “one Lord” by means of the “one faith” mentioned in this verse.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In conclusion, there is unity in the one Lord in whom believers place their one faith expressed in one baptism signifying their identification in his death and resurrection. This verse revolves around the second person of the Trinity.</p>
<p><strong>4:6.</strong> “one God and Father of all.” This is the third triad and it speaks of God the Father. This marks the climax, for God is the one unifying factor in both testaments, in spite of the fact that many gods are honored in the world. … God is further described as the God and Father “of all,” which refers not to all humans but to all believers (John 1:12; Gal 3:26). This is substantiated in the present context because Paul is exhorting Christians, and not all humans, to preserve the unity.</p>
<p>Regarding the further identification of God, there are three parts. First, he is over (ἐπί) all, indicating his sovereign position over all believers. … Second, not only is God sovereign in all believers’ lives, he also works through (δία) all of them. Here the emphasis is on God’s immanence. … Finally, God is in all believers (ἐν πᾶσιν̓ ἡμῖν). This signifies the indwelling Spirit …, his intimate presence. <a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<section class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Harold Hoehner, <em>Ephesians: an Exegetical Commentary</em> (Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 2002), 513–520.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA[History of the KJV-Only movement within Fundamentalism]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/03/11/history-of-the-kjvo-movement-within-fundamentalism/"/>
	<updated>2013-03-11T11:25:00-06:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/03/11/history-of-the-kjvo-movement-within-fundamentalism</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last Saturday I presented a lecture on the history of the King James Only movement within Fundamentalism. The <a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/KJV-Only-Movement-History/">slides are now available</a>.</p>
<p>The lecture was based on an article by Jeff Straub titled “Fundamentalism and the King James Version: How a Venerable English Translation Became a Litmus Test for Orthodoxy.” There is more research that I’d like to do in this area at a future date, but for now, this is as far as I’ve gone with the history of the movement.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
	<title type="html"><![CDATA['That Inestimable Treasure': The History of the English Bible]]></title>
	<link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/03/09/history-of-the-english-bible/"/>
	<updated>2013-03-09T12:00:00-07:00</updated>
	<id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/03/09/history-of-the-english-bible</id>
	<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post contains my lecture notes for a guest lecture during a block class on Bibliology at <a href="http://www.foundationbaptistcollege.ca/">Foundation Baptist College</a> given on March 9, 2013.</em></p>
<blockquote>
<p>But among all our joys, there was no one that more filled our hearts, than the blessed continuance of the preaching of God’s sacred Word among us; which is that inestimable treasure, which excelleth all the riches of the earth; because the fruit thereof extendeth itself, not only to the time spent in this transitory world, but directeth and disposeth men unto that eternal happiness which is above in heaven.<a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Readers of the English Bible have had the privilege of “the blessed continuance of the preaching of God’s sacred Word” now for centuries, a blessing that is dependent upon popular access to reliable English translations. At the time that the King James translators wrote these words, there were a handful of English translations available to the relatively small proportion of the world’s population that spoke English.</p>
<p>Today, those circumstances have changed. Thanks to the growth of the British Empire in the Victorian era and today’s trend toward globalization, English now serves as the trade language for the world. This burgeoning market of English readers has created a demand for updated translations, and today there is such a proliferation of English Bibles on the market that publishers now use slick marketing campaigns as they Compete for readership.</p>
<p>This lecture will attempt to explain how we arrived at this point from such humble beginnings. <!-- Include some learning objectives and more survey thoughts here about the overall outline of the article --></p>
<p>The history of the English Bible divides into three eras:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Medieval period (ca. 700–1500)</li>
<li>The English Reformation to the 19th century (ca. 1500–1900)</li>
<li>The 20th and 21st centuries (1901–2013)</li>
</ol>
<!-- more -->
<h2 id="the-medieval-period-ca.-7001500">1. The Medieval period (ca. 700–1500)</h2>
<h3 id="early-christian-heritage-of-the-british-isles">1.1. Early Christian heritage of the British Isles</h3>
<p>The story of the English Christianity begins under the Roman empire. Christian influence can be found in England as early as the first and second centuries<a href="#fn2" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref2"><sup>2</sup></a>, although it is unknown how Christianity arrived. These early Christians were wiped out when the Angles, Saxons, and Jutes pushed the Romans out of England during the early 5th century. Christianity carried on in the regions of Ireland and Scotland during this time under the leadership of men such as Patrick (5th century) in Ireland and Columba (6th century) in Scotland.</p>
<p>Eventually, Christianity reappeared in England in two competing streams. Missionaries from Scotland were first to arrive, establishing Celtic Christianity. Meanwhile, Roman Christianity was reestablished by Augustine of Canterbury (601–604), who was commissioned by Pope Gregory I (590–604).</p>
<p>Celtic Christianity established itself first in Lindisfarne (known as “the Holy Island”), under the leadership of Aidan ca. A.D. 635. The Celtic monks played an important role in the history of the English Bible and the history of educated Europe. The Lindisfarne monks produced the renowned <em>Lindisfarne Gospels,</em> a beautifully illuminated Latin edition that enabled them to preserve the knowledge of Latin after it was otherwise lost in continental Europe.</p>
<h3 id="medieval-english-bibles">1.2. Medieval English Bibles</h3>
<p>The language of the medieval church in the British Isles was Latin, but a few individuals translated portions of scripture into the common English tongue of the day:</p>
<ul>
<li>Around A.D. 650, Caedmon paraphrased parts of Genesis, Exodus, and Daniel. His work represents an early example of Anglo-Saxon poetry.</li>
<li>Around A.D. 735, Bede the Historian (primarily remembered for his <em>Historia ecclesiastica gentis Anglorum,</em> “The Ecclesiastical History of the English People”) translated parts of the Gospels</li>
<li>In the late 800s, King Alfred the Great translated some of the Psalms and the 10 Commandments into Anglo-Saxon.</li>
<li>From A.D. 955–1020, Aelfric translated various books of the Bible into the English of his day.</li>
<li>In 1325, Richard Rolle and William of Shoreham translate psalms into metrical verse.</li>
</ul>
<!-- Timeline, and this section, needs more detail -->
<h3 id="john-wycliffe-and-the-lollards">1.3. John Wycliffe and the Lollards</h3>
<!-- Based on Cook, lectures 4 p 7 -->
<p>John Wycliffe was the great English reformer who predates the Reformation proper by 150 years and has very little help. He reaches a number of the same conclusions that Luther and Calvin would make much later. He lives from ca. 1320 to 1384, during the time of the Black Plague in England. He lives in a time of clerical ignorance, and desires to teach people to read the Bible for themselves. This is also during the period of the Babylonian Captivity of the papacy.</p>
<p>He gained his degree from Oxford, and preaches against the pope as the Anti-Christ at a young age. He writes a number of tracts against the pope, and sends young men to go from town to town to preach his doctrines. They were called the Lollards. One reason he was successful was his patronage of John of Gaunt, a relative of the King. In 1381 he drew up 12 theses declaring that the doctrine of the RCC was unscriptural, and then he began to translate the Bible into English. He did not know Greek and Hebrew, so he translated from the Latin.</p>
<p>Wycliffe’s theology can be found in his <em>Summa Theologica.</em> His core beliefs were as follows:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The church consists of the elect. This was a novel concept to the church, which viewed all as subject to the pope.</li>
<li>He viewed the papacy as the anti-christ.</li>
<li>He viewed the priesthood as scandalous and immoral and incapable of effecting salvation.</li>
<li>Transubstantiation is a myth.</li>
<li>The scriptures are of supreme authority.</li>
</ol>
<p>He was very literal in his translation of scripture. He was more successful in Bohemia because of John Huss than he was in England. The Lollards were interesting people who would leave sections of the Scriptures in different villages. In 1401, Parliament passed an act aimed at the Lollards that gave the right to the civil authorities to burn heretics at the stake. Eventually, the Lollards who remained were incorporated into the Puritan movement. They were opposed to images, pilgrimages, etc.</p>
<h2 id="the-english-reformation-to-the-19th-century-ca.-15001900">2. The English Reformation to the 19th century (ca. 1500–1900)</h2>
<h3 id="william-tyndale-ca.-1494-1536">2.1. William Tyndale (ca. 1494-1536)</h3>
<p>The lineage of the modern English Bible begins with the work of William Tyndale (<em>ca.</em> 1494–1536). Below are a few significant dates for Tyndale’s life.</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">1512</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Graduates with Oxford BA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">1515</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Graduates with Oxford MA</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">1525-35</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Translates the Bible</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<!-- Brent Cook, lectures 5 p 7: -->
<p>Tyndale came from an obscure childhood. The one note we have from his youth is that while young he had read that King Alfred had produced a translation of the Bible. He went to Oxford, unlike the others. He was disturbed that he was not encouraged to read the Scriptures. He complained that they were not allowed to look at the Scriptures until after 8 or 9 years of indoctrination in doctrines which prevented understanding of the Bible. In 1516, he came to Cambridge. He probably joined the meetings at the White Horse Inn. He later became a private tutor for Sir John Walsh of Gloucestershire. He seems to have convinced Sir John that a good translation of the Bible was necessary.</p>
<p>He went outdoors to preach in the open air, and discovered that the Catholics created a rumor about him and attempted to ruin him. Distressed, he returned to Cambridge where he met an old scholar named William Latimer (no relation to Hugh). Latimer said to him: “Do you not know that the Pope is very anti-Christ, whom the Scriptures speaketh of? But beware of what you say, for if you say so publicly you will lose your life.” Tyndale never overcame this.</p>
<p>He was convinced that what England needed was a new translation of the Scripture. He found a man named Humphrey Monmouth who was interested in a translation of the Scripture and supported him. However, Monmouth advised him that England was not the best place to produce a translation. In 1524, Tyndale left all his goods with Monmouth and set sail for Hamburg. He did not know it, but he would never return. He is hard to track down at this point, because he is forever on the run. He printed Bibles in Cologne, but then quickly fled to Worms where he produced his first edition of the New Testament. He found German merchants who were all too glad to smuggle his Bibles into England. Eventually he wound up in Antwerp on the coast where it was easier to smuggle the Bibles back to England. In 1526 Bishop Tunstall ordered that all Tyndale Bibles were to be burned. It was too little too late. He wrote many other works, commentaries, The Obedience of a Christian Man, The Practice of the Prelates, and a great Dialogue with Thomas More. In all, he produced three editions of the New Testament until 1535. He then fell victim to a plot to lure him out of hiding. He was imprisoned in the Low Countries and ignored. Here he died on October 6, 1536. He was strangled and then his body burned at the stake. His last words, as they come down to us, were “Lord, Open the King of England’s eyes.” Ironically, his third edition was printed on the King’s press in England. Approximately 4/5 of this translation made it into the KJV.</p>
<h3 id="the-king-james-bible">2.2. The King James Bible</h3>
<p>The KJV was produced during the reign of James I of England. James I was already James VI of Scotland. His reign over England and Scotland lasted from the death of Elizabeth I in 1603 to his death in 1625.</p>
<p>At his ascension, England was plagued with a variety of problems, and there was religious unrest between the Calvinist Puritans and the Catholics. The Calvinists and Puritans thought he would favor them since he was Scottish after all. The Catholics thought he would favor them because his mother Mary was a good Catholic. In reality, the side he took was his own. He believed in the “divine right” of the monarchy, whereby the authority of the despot is directly given by God and he cannot be questioned. This view is that God ordained human government in the person of an individual king who is responsible for the nation. We see this view expressed in the actions of Richard Bancroft, archbishop of Canterbury during this time:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The tension between the prelates of the official church and the Puritans grew during James’s reign. In 1604, Richard Bancroft, archbishop of Canterbury, had a series of canons approved in which it was affirmed that episcopal hierarchy was an institution of divine origin, and that without it there could be no true church. This implied a rejection of the many Protestant churches on the Continent that had no bishops, and therefore Puritans saw in it a step towards breaking away from Protestant ties in order to reintroduce Catholicism in England. Besides this, several other canons approved on the archbishop’s insistence were clearly directed against Puritans.<a href="#fn3" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref3"><sup>3</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The story of the KJV begins when the Puritans came to James in 1604 with a “Millenary Petition” asking to move England in a Protestant direction. They hoped to establish Presbyterianism, institute freedom of worship, etc. They met him at the Hampton Court, and he refused all their requests (except the production of the <em>Authorized Version</em>).</p>
<p>James was not involved in the work of translation himself, but he did take an interest in it. Shortly after Hampton Court he instructed Archbishop Richard Bancroft (no friend of the Puritans, as we have seen) to contact all English churchmen requesting that they seek church positions for the translators, thus assuring them an income.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Right trusty and well beloved, we greet you well. Whereas we have appointed certain learned men, to the number of 4 and 50, for the translating of the Bible, and in this number, divers of them have either no ecclesiastical preferment at all, or else so very small, as the same is far unmeet for men of their deserts and yet we in ourself in any convenient time cannot well remedy it, therefor we do hereby require you, that presently you write in our name as well to the Archbishop of York, as to the rest of the bishops of the province of Cant.[erbury] signifying unto them, that we do well, and straitly charge everyone of them … that (all excuses set apart) when we prebend or parsonage … shall next upon any occasion happen to be void … we may commend for the same some such of the learned men, as we shall think fit to be preferred unto it … Given unto our signet at our palace of West.[minister] on 2 and 20 July , in the 2nd year of our reign of England, France, and of Ireland, and of Scotland xxxvii.“<a href="#fn4" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref4"><sup>4</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<h4 id="translation-process">2.2.1. Translation process</h4>
<p>The work of translation took place in two stages:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>A Translation Committee translated sections of the Bible from 1604–1608.</li>
<li>The completed translation was evaluated by a General Committee of Review from 1609–1611.</li>
<li>The original printing of the Authorized Version was published by Robert Barker, the King’s Printer, in 1611 as a complete folio Bible. It was sold looseleaf for ten shillings, or bound for twelve.</li>
</ol>
<h4 id="publication-history">2.2.2. Publication history</h4>
<p>By current standards, seventeenth-century book printing appears informal and unstandardized, and the early production history of the KJV includes a variety of well-known printer’s errors. These errors ranged in severity from comical typos (such as the “Printer’s Bible” and “Vinegar Bible”) to serious omissions (such as the “Wicked Bible”).</p>
<p>The publication history of the KJV can also be divided into stages:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>KJV produced by the King’s Printer (1612–1617).</strong> “This short period sees no fewer than thirty printings of the KJB. Careless mistakes continue to be found and deliberate changes start to creep in.”<a href="#fn5" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref5"><sup>5</sup></a></li>
<li><strong>KJV produced by the Cambridge and Oxford University Presses (1629–1760).</strong> “This period marks the transition in the printing rights from the King’s Printer to the hands of the two university presses. it is a period in which the commercial benefits of being scholarly were occasionally realized. Both Oxford and Cambridge published two major editions (cambridge, 1629 and 1638; Oxford, 1675 and 1679). the great care of the editors of the cambridge editions contrasts sharply with that of the King’s Printer.”<a href="#fn6" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref6"><sup>6</sup></a></li>
<li><strong>Attempts to standardize the KJV text (1762–1769).</strong> “By the mid-eighteenth century the wide variation in the various modernized reprints of the KJB, combined with all the notorious misprints, had reached the proportion of a scandal. eventually, the Universities of Oxford (Benjamin Blayney in 1769) and Cambridge (F. S. Parris in 1762) both sought to produce an updated standard text.”<a href="#fn7" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref7"><sup>7</sup></a> Eventually, the Oxford standardization by Blayney became the accepted standard for the KJV text.</li>
</ol>
<p>Edited by Benjamin Blayney, the 1769 edition sought to overcome the numerous variants introduced by printing errors since 1611 and has since become the text of all modern editions of the KJV. To understand the types of changes Blayney made, consider these passages from the 1611 and 1769 text below (examples from Wikipedia).</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>1 Cor. 13:1-3 (1611)</strong> <sup>1</sup> Though I speake with the tongues of men &amp; of Angels, and haue not charity, I am become as sounding brasse or a tinkling cymbal. <sup>2</sup> And though I haue the gift of prophesie, and vnderstand all mysteries and all knowledge: and though I haue all faith, so that I could remooue mountaines, and haue no charitie, I am nothing. <sup>3</sup> And though I bestowe all my goods to feede the poore, and though I giue my body to bee burned, and haue not charitie, it profiteth me nothing.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>1 Cor. 13:1-3 (1769)</strong> <sup>1</sup> Though I speak with the tongues of men and of angels, and have not charity, I am become as sounding brass, or a tinkling cymbal. <sup>2</sup> And though I have the gift of prophecy, and understand all mysteries, and all knowledge; and though I have all faith, so that I could remove mountains, and have not charity, I am nothing. <sup>3</sup> And though I bestow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and have not charity, it profiteth me nothing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The KJV eventually became the dominant English text. Wong notes that Blayney’s edition became dominant shortly after publication:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Since the beginning of the nineteenth century, almost all printings of the KJB have derived from the 1769 Oxford text—generally without Blayney’s variant notes and cross references, and commonly excluding the Apocrypha.<a href="#fn8" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref8"><sup>8</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="the-20th-and-21st-centuries-19012011">3. The 20th and 21st centuries (1901–2011)</h2>
<p>[<em>Note:</em> The material in this section has been updated in my newer post on <a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/12/15/the-history-of-the-english-bible-since-the-20th-century/">The History of the English Bible Since the 20th Century</a>]</p>
<p>Around the turn of the 19th century, a consensus began to develop that the archaic language of the KJV needed updating. This produced a number of different attempts to either 1) revise the KJV itself, or 2) produce a new translation using more contemporary English. Some of the more prominent attempts under each of these categories are listed below:</p>
<ul>
<li>Proposed revisions of the KJV
<ol type="1">
<li>British Revised Version (RV; 1881–1885)</li>
<li>American Standard Version (ASV; 1901)</li>
<li>Revised Standard Version (RSV; 1952)</li>
<li>New King James Version (NKJV; 1982)</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Fresh translations
<ol type="1">
<li>Jerusalem Bible (1966)</li>
<li>New American Bible and New English Bible (1970)</li>
<li>New American Standard Bible (1971)</li>
<li>Good News Bible (Today’s English Version; 1976)</li>
<li>New International Version (1978; minor update 1984)</li>
<li>New Jerusalem Bible (1985)</li>
<li>New Revised Standard Version (1990)</li>
<li>Update to the NASB (1995)</li>
<li>English Standard Version (2001)</li>
<li>Today’s New International Version (2005)</li>
<li>NET Bible (2005)</li>
<li>New International Version (2011 update)</li>
</ol></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="the-new-international-version-19562011">3.1. The New International Version (1956–2011)</h3>
<p>At this point, we will refer to a handout titled “Controversies relating to the NIV: Summary” which I wrote on Sept 7, 2009.</p>
<h3 id="other-modern-translations">3.2. Other modern translations</h3>
<p>For some brief background on the ESV and HCSB, see William Combs’ article in the bibliography, particularly pp. 11–15 and 21–22.</p>
<h2 id="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement</h2>
<p>Portions of these notes were drawn from my class notes taken during two courses (Church History 1 and Church History 2) with Dr. Brenton Cook at Bob Jones University during 2008–2009.</p>
<h2 id="additional-resources">Additional Resources</h2>
<h3 id="online-media">Online media</h3>
<p>The material in this lecture is designed to be supplemented by an <a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/English-Bible/">interactive timeline project</a> which I’ve worked on as a hobby since mid-2011. Many of the events described here will show up in there, with links to additional reading on Wikipedia.</p>
<h3 id="select-bibliography">Select Bibliography</h3>
<p>Brake, Donald L. <em>A Visual History of the English Bible: The Tumultuous Tale of the World’s Bestselling Book.</em> Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Books, 2008.</p>
<p>McGrath, Alister E. <em>In the Beginning: The Story of the King James Bible and How It Changed a Nation, a Language, and a Culture.</em> 1st ed. New York: Doubleday, 2001.</p>
<p>Nicolson, Adam. <em>God’s Secretaries: The Making of the King James Bible.</em> 1st ed. New York: HarperCollins, 2003.</p>
<p>Norton, David. <em>A Textual History of the King James Bible.</em>Cambridge: University Press, 2004.</p>
<p>Wong, Simon. “Which King James Bible Are We Referring To?” <em>Bible Translator</em> 62, no. 1 (January 2011): 1–11. <a href="http://www.ubs-translations.org/fileadmin/publications/tbt/technical/BT-62-1-Wong.pdf" class="uri">http://www.ubs-translations.org/fileadmin/publications/tbt/technical/BT-62-1-Wong.pdf</a></p>
<section class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Epistle Dedicatory, King James Bible.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saint_Alban">Alban</a> was martyred in England sometime between A.D. 209 and 259.<a href="#fnref2">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Gonzalez, Justo L. <em>The Story of Christianity: The Reformation to the Present Day.</em> Vol. 2. 1st ed. HarperOne, 1985., 152.<a href="#fnref3">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Walleshinsky, David (1975). The People’s Almanac. Doubleday &amp; Company Inc., p. 235<a href="#fnref4">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Wong, Simon. “Which King James Bible Are We Referring To?” <em>Bible Translator</em> 62, no. 1 (January 2011): 4.<a href="#fnref5">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>Ibid., 5.<a href="#fnref6">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>Ibid., 6.<a href="#fnref7">↩</a></p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>Ibid., 7.<a href="#fnref8">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
