<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Church History | DuncanJohnson.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/categories/church-history/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-16T16:13:13-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Johnson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Pentecostal Outpourings: Revival and the Reformed Tradition]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2016/05/20/book-review-pentecostal-outpourings-revival-and-the-reformed-tradition/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-20T17:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2016/05/20/book-review-pentecostal-outpourings-revival-and-the-reformed-tradition</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2016/05/Pentecostal-Outpourings-682x1024.jpg"><img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2016/05/Pentecostal-Outpourings-200x300.jpg" alt="Pentecostal Outpourings" /></a></p>
<p>Smart, Robert Davis, Michael A. G. Haykin, and Ian Hugh Clary, eds. <em>Pentecostal Outpourings: Revival and the Reformed Tradition.</em> Grand Rapids, MI: Reformation Heritage Books, 2016. ISBN 9781601784339. 280 pages.</p>
<p>Nearly all Christians say that they desire “true revival,” but few agree on what that phrase means. Evangelicals sometimes distinguish between “revival” and “reformation,” associating the former with individual spiritual renewal (usually through mass conversions) and the latter with outward societal change. Furthermore, many evangelicals will contrast “true (or genuine) revival” with “false revival.” Iain Murray captures this contrast in his well-known work entitled <em>Revival and Revivalism.</em> What is it that distinguishes between true revival and the excesses of revivalism? Should Christians pray for revival? How should they seek it, and what should they expect when it comes?</p>
<p>These questions are particularly vexing for those within the Reformed tradition. <em>Pentecostal Outpourings: Revival and the Reformed Tradition</em> brings together a coterie of Reformed historians to argue that true revival is not merely compatible with Calvinistic theology, but that historical revivals have been heavily influenced by Reformed preaching and represents a consistent understanding of the true gospel. Despite the real and lasting results of these revivals, the historical record is difficult to interpret because true revivals have often included mixed reports of unnerving enthusiasm or manipulative revivalistic tactics. Parsing these confusing elements requires a foundational understanding of true revival, defined as follows by Robert Davis Smart in the introduction:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Pentecostal Outpourings</em> demonstrates that revival is a sovereign gift from God in which, for a special season, His normal and true work of advancing His kingdom is sped up or quickened so that more is accomplished through His servants in a shorter period of time. Revivals cannot be merited by us but have been secured by another—Jesus Christ. Jesus tells His disciples that His righteous life and atoning death won for us “the promise of My Father” (Luke 24:49; Acts 1:4). When Jesus ascended to the Father and sat down at the right hand of God, He poured out His Holy Spirit at Pentecost. This once-for-all historical and redemptive event was not the last time Christ poured out His Spirit in redemptive history. Subsequent outpourings of the Holy Spirit, working by and with the Word, are reviewed in this volume in order that we may seek God earnestly to revive His church once again soon.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Each chapter in <em>Pentecostal Outpourings</em> focuses on the history of revivals within a particular area and denominational tradition and is written by a specialist. As a result, the chapters provide detailed and reliable historical scholarship tracing the impact of revivals, usually beginning with the “Evangelical Revival” or “Great Awakening” and carrying forward through twentieth century. In some cases, chapters conclude with an extended theological analysis of the historical events (<em>e.g.</em>, the chapter by Eifon Evans on the Welsh Calvinistic Methodists). Each well-written chapter includes numerous historical examples from individual conversion narratives, the writings of revival preachers, and contemporary historical records. A few of these memorable stories include the remarkable revival stirred by the harsh preaching of “crazy James Glendinning” in Ireland, the eventual misappropriation of Jonathan Edwards’s revival apologetic by later revivalists, and Andrew Fuller’s growth out of hyper-Calvinism to the zealously evangelistic Calvinism that eventually led to William Carey’s missionary endeavors. Of course, these are but a few highlights, and the time would fail me to tell you about the countless ordinary believers who came to lasting faith in Christ through the revival preaching that is recounted in this volume. To fully appreciate these revival stories, you just have to read the book.</p>
<p>Many similarities stand out in these accounts of revivals which took place in vastly different locations, among divergent denominational traditions, and at different times. It is immediately obvious that true revival is no respecter of denominations. It occurs, often without warning or harbinger, wherever and whenever God pleases according to His sovereign plan. Genuine and lasting revival cannot be manufactured, yet many times it does occur amongst people who have earnestly prayed for it. Unfortunately, it can be difficult to distinguish between true revival and excessive emotional enthusiasm, which many times occur simultaneously. Careful pastors who are aware of this repeatedly seek to steer their people towards the Scriptures in an effort to curb excesses.</p>
<p>Those who read this book will be forced to reflect on their own relationship to God’s providential work. Evangelical Christians will come away from this work with a renewed longing for genuine revival, resulting in earnest prayer and renewed passion for faithful preaching and teaching of the Bible. But I suspect that even readers who are not evangelicals may be drawn to this volume, perhaps curious about evangelical claims of divine intervention. Although this book alone won’t be sufficient to overcome agnostic doubts, such readers will find such striking similarities in the genuine revival accounts that they may be driven further in a search to evaluate the claims of the Christian gospel itself.</p>
<p><em>Pentecostal Outpourings</em> is available for purchase from Amazon and CBD. Purchasing a copy using one of these links below will earn me a small affiliate commission:</p>
<ul>
<li>eBook:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Pentecostal-Outpourings-Revival-Reformed-Tradition-ebook/dp/B01CZA6OZC/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=&amp;ref_=tmm_kin_swatch_0&amp;sr=&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20&amp;linkId=71228063385169a8e2a4256423fa37ec">Amazon Kindle (USA)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B01CZA6OZC/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B01CZA6OZC&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon Kindle (Canada)</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li>Paperback:
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=784339">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Pentecostal-Outpourings-Revival-Reformed-Tradition/dp/1601784333/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20&amp;linkId=f8d24579ffe4229976989e01f889b170">Amazon.com (USA)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/1601784333/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=1601784333&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca (Canada)</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<!-- more -->
<p><strong>Table of Contents:</strong></p>
<p>Preface — Steve Lawson<br />
Introduction — Robert Davis Smart</p>
<ol type="I">
<li><strong>Revival in the British Isles</strong></li>
</ol>
<ol type="1">
<li>“The Power of Heaven in the Word of Life”: Welsh Calvinistic Methodism and Revival — Eifon Evans</li>
<li>“Melting the Ice of a Long Winter”: Revival and Irish Dissent — Ian Hugh Clary</li>
<li>“The Lord Is Doing Great Things and Answering Prayer Everywhere”: The Revival of the Calvinistic Baptists in the Long Eighteenth Century — Michael A. G. Haykin</li>
<li>Revival: A Scottish Presbyterian Perspective — Iain Campbell</li>
</ol>
<ol start="2" type="I">
<li><strong>Revival in America</strong></li>
</ol>
<ol start="5" type="1">
<li>Edwards’s Revival Instinctive and Apologetic in American Presbyterianism: Planted, Grown, and Faded — Robert Davis Smart</li>
<li>“The Glorious Work of God”: Revival among Congregationalists in the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries — Peter Beck</li>
<li>Baptist Revivals in America in the Eighteenth Century — Tom Nettles</li>
<li>Dutch Reformed Church in America (the 18th century) — Joel Beeke</li>
</ol>
<p>A Concluding Word—A Call to Seek God for Revival Today — Robert Davis Smart</p>
<p><strong>Editors and Contributors</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Editors
<ul>
<li>Ian Hugh Clary is a research and teaching assistant and fellow of the Andrew Fuller Center for Baptist Studies. He lectures in church history at Redeemer University College, Ancaster, Ontario, and in theology at Munster Bible College, Cork, Ireland, and is an associate minister at West Toronto Baptist Church, Toronto.</li>
<li>Michael A. G. Haykin is professor of church history and biblical spirituality at The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary in Louisville, Kentucky, and is the director of the Andrew Fuller Center for Baptist Studies based on the campus of Southern.</li>
<li>Robert Davis Smart is lead pastor of Christ Church of Bloomington, Illinois. He teaches part time at seminaries, with an emphasis on revival and spiritual formation.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Contributors
<ul>
<li>Peter Beck is associate professor of Christian studies and director of the honors program at Charleston Southern University. Additionally, he currently serves as lead pastor of Doorway Baptist Church in North Charleston, South Carolina.</li>
<li>Joel R. Beeke is the president of Puritan Reformed Theological Seminary in Grand Rapids, Michigan, where he also serves as professor of systematic theology and homiletics. In addition, he is a pastor of the Heritage Netherlands Reformed Congregation.</li>
<li>Iain D. Campbell is minister of Point Free Church of Scotland on the Isle of Lewis. Eifion Evans is a retired Presbyterian minister, having pastored churches in Wales and Northern Ireland.</li>
<li>Tom Nettles is a retired professor of historical theology from The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary in Louisville, Kentucky. He presently serves as senior professor of historical theology.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><em>If you’d like to comment on this review, please post your thoughts on <a href="https://www.amazon.com/review/R2NBQZ2MK2AQX4">Amazon.com</a> or <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1640977166">GoodReads</a>. Thanks!</em></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Compilation of Resources for #Whitefield300]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/12/21/a-compilation-of-resources-for-whitefield300/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-21T15:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/12/21/a-compilation-of-resources-for-whitefield300</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/12/whitefield.jpg"></p>
<p>On 16 December 1714 (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_Style_and_New_Style_dates">O.S.</a>), George Whitefield was born at the Bell Inn, Southgate Street, Gloucester. This past week, his birthday was commemorated on Twitter with the hashtag <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Whitefield300">#Whitefield300</a> at the suggestion of <a href="https://twitter.com/ThomasSKidd/status/539919555921862656">Whitefield biographer Thomas Kidd</a>.</p>
<p>I used <a href="http://ifttt.com/">IFTTT</a> to archive the tweet stream. At first, I was just appending the tweets to an Evernote file. When I set that up, I didn’t know that IFTTT is limited to only 30 updates to Evernote per hour, which obviously didn’t work out too well once the volume picked up on the morning of December 16. Once I realized what was going on, I set up a Google Sheet to collect the tweet stream, and this seems to have been much more reliable.</p>
<p>Below is my attempt to compile some of the resources available on Whitefield, including links to my Google Sheet and Evernote file. If I have missed anything of significance, please drop me a line (email <a href="mailto:djohnson@foundationbaptistcollege.ca">duncan-at-duncanjohnson-dot-ca</a> or tweet <a href="https://twitter.com/dtjohnso">@dtjohnso</a>) and I’ll be glad to update the list.</p>
<!-- more -->
<h2 id="whitefield300-tweets">#Whitefield300 Tweets</h2>
<p>The tweet stream includes many Whitefield quotations, as well as links to other resources.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Whitefield300">Twitter search</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23Whitefield300&amp;mode=photos">Photos</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1guKMzlGxnaRRhTz9Pv0PQFzaiOo2U7lhD3PDu4dLOCI/edit?usp=sharing">Google Sheet</a> (includes tweets from December 16, 2014 at 09:18AM UTC-7 onwards)</li>
<li><a href="http://www.evernote.com/l/ACi9WKKF5AtEE7JczIRRB3RlihJZu9cc5rs/">Evernote</a> (includes some early tweets that do not appear in the Google Sheet)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conferences">Conferences</h2>
<p>There were three conferences this year commemorating Whitefield. I attended and enjoyed the conference at Southern.</p>
<ul>
<li>“George Whitefield at 300: An International Tercentenary Conference” at Pembroke College, Oxford, 25–27 June 2014 - <a href="http://www.mwrc.ac.uk/whitefield-conference/">Official page</a>, followup post by <a href="http://earlyamericanists.com/2014/07/10/guest-post-george-whitefield-at-300-conference-recap/">Jessica Parr</a></li>
<li>“Whitefield and the Great Awakening, Andrew Fuller Center for Baptist Studies 8th Annual Conference” at Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, 21–22 October 2014 - <a href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/11/whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference/">My preview post</a>, <a href="http://www.andrewfullercenter.org/blog/2014/11/video-and-audio-of-whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference/">Free video and audio of all the sessions</a></li>
<li>“George Whitefield at 300: Remembering the Eighteenth Century’s Greatest Revivalist” at Baylor University, 13–14 November 2014 - <a href="http://www.baylorisr.org/2014/11/whitefield-symposium/">Official page</a>, <a href="http://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL0JmtbsEea3iQg4PphJ7luoOMjYxsO0Ns">Video of panel sessions</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="blog-posts">Blog posts</h2>
<p><a href="http://thegospelcoalition.org/blogs/tgc/2014/01/09/the-science-of-sound-whitefields-massive-crowds/">“The Science of Sound: Whitefield’s Massive Crowds,”</a> Accessed January 12, 2014.</p>
<p>Kidd, Thomas. <a href="http://us3.campaign-archive1.com/?u=393885e6de8bef994ad9a4c3b&amp;id=97fb150c7e&amp;e=f6930787a8">“George Whitefield and Slavery,”</a> June 19, 2014. Accessed June 19, 2014.</p>
<p><a href="http://digitalexhibits.ptsem.edu/exhibits/show/the-grand-itinerant---george-w">The Grand Itinerant: George Whitefield at 300</a>. A digital collection of Whitefield-related materials collected by Princeton Theological Seminary. Includes a number of original documents, including one of Whitefield’s hand-written journals.</p>
<h2 id="lecture-video-audio">Lecture Video &amp; Audio</h2>
<p>Trueman, Carl. <a href="http://vimeo.com/111740829">“George Whitefield: Preacher, Celebrity, Saint”</a>, 2014.</p>
<p>Kidd, Thomas S. <a href="https://vimeo.com/93374328">“George Whitefield: Lessons from the Eighteenth Century’s Greatest Evangelist.”</a> Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, 2014.</p>
<p>A four-session conference, “George Whitefield and the Great Awakening” at West Toronto Baptist Church:</p>
<ul>
<li>Michael Haykin, <a href="http://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?SID=111814161482">George Whitefield and the Great Awakening, Part 1</a></li>
<li>Michael Haykin, <a href="http://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?SID=1118141641352">George Whitefield and the Great Awakening, Q&amp;A</a></li>
<li>Michael Haykin, <a href="http://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?SID=1118141638271">George Whitefield and the Great Awakening, Part 2</a></li>
<li>Ian Clary, <a href="http://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?SID=1118141646520">The Marks of True Conversion: A Sermon of George Whitefield</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="online-journal-and-magazine-articles">Online Journal and Magazine Articles</h2>
<p>Clary, Ian. <a href="https://www.academia.edu/8590577/Pastor-Historian_Arnold_Dallimore_and_the_Writing_of_Whitefield">“Pastor-Historian: Arnold Dallimore and the Writing of Whitefield.”</a> <em>The Reformed Theological Review</em> 73, no. 2 (August 2014): 117–132.</p>
<p>Haykin, Michael A. G. <a href="http://www.thrive-magazine.ca/qry/page.taf?id=27&amp;_function=atcldetail&amp;sbtatcl_uid1=229">“George Whitefield: A Man Of Focus From The Eighteenth Century.”</a> Thrive: The EB Online. Accessed November 24, 2014.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/category/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/"><em>The Southern Baptist Journal of Theology</em> 18, no 2 (Summer 2014)</a> was dedicated to the legacy of Whitefield. Individual articles are linked below:</p>
<ul>
<li>Stephen J. Wellum, <a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/editorial-the-life-and-legacy-of-george-whitefield-1714-1770/">Editorial: “The Life and Legacy of George Whitefield (1714-1770)” by</a></li>
<li>Michael Haykin, <a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/the-christian-life-in-the-thought-of-george-whitefield/">“The Christian Life in the Thought of George Whitefield”</a></li>
<li>Digby James, <a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/who-is-the-greatest-preacher-the-life-and-legacy-of-george-whitefield/">“Who is the Greatest Preacher? The Life and Legacy of George Whitefield”</a></li>
<li>Jeongmo Yoo, <a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/george-whitefields-doctrine-of-christ/">“George Whitefield’s Doctrine of Christ”</a></li>
<li>Lee Gatiss, <a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/george-whitefield-the-angelican-evangelist/">“George Whitefield — The Anglican Evangelist”</a></li>
<li>Introduced and Edited by Michael A. G. Haykin, <a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/writing-to-george-whitefield-a-letter-from-anne-dutton-on-sinless-perfection/">“Writing to George Whitefield: A letter from Anne Dutton on Sinless Perfection”</a></li>
<li>Introduced and Edited by Michael A. G. Haykin, <a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/george-whitefield-sermon-the-indwelling-of-the-spirit-the-common-privilege-of-all-believers/">George Whitefield Sermon: ‘The Indwelling of the Spirit the Common Privilege of All Believers.’</a></li>
<li>Introduced and Edited by Michael A. G. Haykin, <a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/george-whitefield-sermon-christ-the-believers-wisdom-righteousness-sanctification-and-redemption/">George Whitefield Sermon: “Christ, the Believer’s Wisdom, Righteousness, Sanctification and Redemption”</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.sbts.edu/resources/journal-of-theology/sbjt-182-summer-2014/the-sbjt-forum-2/">The SBJT Forum</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Credo magazine did an <a href="http://www.credomag.com/george-whitefield-at-300/">issue titled “George Whitefield at 300.”</a></p>
<h2 id="books">Books</h2>
<h3 id="primary-source-texts">Primary Source Texts</h3>
<p>Gatiss, Lee, ed. <em>The Sermons of George Whitefield.</em> Wheaton, Ill: Crossway, 2012. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/143353245X/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=143353245X&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=532451">CBD</a> or on <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B008YGE8PU/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B008YGE8PU&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle</a>.</p>
<p>Haykin, Michael A. G., ed. <em>The Revived Puritan: The Spirituality of George Whitefield.</em> Classics of Reformed Spirituality. Dundas, Ont: Joshua Press, 2000. Available from <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=400062">CBD</a>.</p>
<h3 id="biographies-and-historical-analysis">Biographies and Historical Analysis</h3>
<p>Belcher, Joseph. <em>George Whitefield: A Biography, with Special Reference to His Labors in America.</em> New York, American Tract Society, 1857. Accessed December 17, 2014. Available at <a href="http://archive.org/details/georgewhitefield00belc">Archive.org</a>.</p>
<p>Dallimore, Arnold A. <em>George Whitefield: God’s Anointed Servant in the Great Revival of the Eighteenth Century.</em> Westchester, Ill.: Crossway Books, 2010. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/1433513412/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=1433513412&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=513411">CBD</a> or on <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00A0XABJM/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00A0XABJM&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle</a>.</p>
<p>———. <em>George Whitefield: The Life and Times of the Great Evangelist of the Eighteenth-Century Revival.</em> 2 vols. London: Banner of Truth Trust, 1970. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0851517307/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0851517307&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=517302">CBD</a>.</p>
<p>Gillies, John. Memoirs of Rev. George Whitefield. Hunt &amp; Noyes, 1839. Accessed December 17, 2014. Available at <a href="http://archive.org/details/memoirsrevgeorg03whitgoog">Archive.org</a>.</p>
<p>Haykin, Michael A. G. <em>Bitesize Biographies: George Whitefield.</em> First edition. Evangelical Press, 2014.</p>
<p>Kidd, Thomas S. <em>George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father.</em> New Haven: Yale University Press, 2014. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0300181620/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0300181620&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=181623">CBD</a> or on <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00O56PTU6/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00O56PTU6&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle</a>. See also <a href="http://www.thegospelcoalition.org/blogs/justintaylor/2014/12/16/an-interview-with-thomas-kidd-on-george-whitefield/">Justin Taylor’s interview with Kidd</a>.</p>
<p>Lambert, Frank. <em>“Pedlar in Divinity”: George Whitefield and the Transatlantic Revivals, 1737-1770.</em> Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 2002. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0691032963/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0691032963&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a>.</p>
<p>Lawson, Steven J. <em>The Evangelistic Zeal of George Whitefield.</em> Orlando, FL: Reformation Trust Publishing, 2014. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/1567693636/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=1567693636&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=693638">CBD</a> or on <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00IJH7B3K/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00IJH7B3K&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle</a>.</p>
<p>Mahaffey, Jerome Dean. <em>Preaching Politics: The Religious Rhetoric of George Whitefield and the Founding of a New Nation.</em> Waco, TX: Baylor University Press, 2007. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/1932792880/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=1932792880&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=792881">CBD</a> or on <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B0019JHD74/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B0019JHD74&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle</a>.</p>
<p>———. <em>The Accidental Revolutionary: George Whitefield and the Creation of America.</em> Waco, TX: Baylor University Press, 2011. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/1602583919/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=1602583919&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=583917">CBD</a> or on <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00IGDXJ1A/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00IGDXJ1A&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle</a>.</p>
<p>Noll, Mark. <em>The Rise of Evangelicalism: The Age of Edwards, Whitefield, and the Wesleys.</em> A History of Evangelicalism: People, Movements and Ideas in the English-Speaking World. Downers Grove, IL: InterVarsity Press, 2003. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0830838910/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0830838910&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=838912">CBD</a>.</p>
<p>Parr, Jessica M. <em>Inventing George Whitefield: Race, Revivalism, and the Making of a Religious Icon.</em> Jackson: University Press of Mississippi, forthcoming 2015.</p>
<p>Piper, John. <em>Seeing Beauty and Saying Beautifully: The Power of Poetic Effort in the Work of George Herbert, George Whitefield, and C.S. Lewis.</em> Wheaton, IL: Crossway, 2014. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/1433542943/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=1433542943&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=542947">CBD</a> or on <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00KCS49WK/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00KCS49WK&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle</a>.</p>
<p>Ryle, J. C. <em>The Christian Leaders of England in the Eighteenth Century.</em> London, C.J. Thynne &amp; Jarvis, 1868. Accessed December 17, 2014. Available at <a href="http://archive.org/details/christianleaders00ryleuoft">Archive.org</a>.</p>
<p>Stout, Harry S. <em>The Divine Dramatist: George Whitefield and the Rise of Modern Evangelicalism.</em> Grand Rapids, Mich: Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1991. Available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0802801544/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0802801544&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=0154">CBD</a> or on <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00352M9OK/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00352M9OK&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle</a>.</p>
<p>[Update Jan 27, 2015: Added link to Baylor ISR conference session videos.]</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Notes - Baptists Through the Centuries by David Bebbington]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/12/03/book-notes-baptists-through-the-centuries-by-david-bebbington/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-03T15:47:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/12/03/book-notes-baptists-through-the-centuries-by-david-bebbington</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2014/12/tn_4850.png"></p>
<p>Bebbington, David W. <em>Baptists through the Centuries: A History of a Global People.</em> Waco, TX: Baylor University Press, 2010.</p>
<p>This book was runner-up in my textbook adoption process for my Baptist history course. I have not yet read this book in full, but I have found portions of this book to be helpful as I prepared lectures. I chose not to select this book as required course reading for two reasons:</p>
<ol type="a">
<li>Published as it is by Baylor University Press, it costs slightly more than Leonard.</li>
<li>Bebbington follows a <em>synthetic</em> rather than <em>chronological</em> approach to the details of Baptist history. He describes the synthetic approach in the paragraph quoted below.</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>“It is primarily a work of synthesis that attempts to put the pieces of the puzzle into an intelligible framework. Its approach, therefore, is topical. In accordance with the maxim that it is better to study problems rather than periods, each chapter addresses an issue in Baptist history. … A second feature of the book is its effort to set the problems at hand in a wider context than Baptist history. Baptists did not exist alone, and so the analysis gives space to the broader influences—intellectual, social, and political—that played on religious developments. … The third aspect worth mentioning is the principle of organization. Countries are not kept apart, for that misrepresents the reality of the past. For all the contrasts between different nations, Baptists traveled between them, read each other’s writings, and corresponded across oceans. What happened in one part of the world was often duplicated elsewhere.” (pp. 4–5)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This approach is self-evident when you look at the chapter titles, listed below:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Introduction</li>
<li>Roots in the Reformation</li>
<li>Anabaptists and Baptists</li>
<li>Particular and General Baptists in the Seventeenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists and Revival in the Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Divisions among Baptists in the Nineteenth Century</li>
<li>Theological Polarization among Baptists</li>
<li>Baptists and the Social Gospel</li>
<li>Gospel and Race among Baptists</li>
<li>Women in Baptist Life</li>
<li>Church, Ministry, and Sacraments among Baptists</li>
<li>Baptists and Religious Liberty</li>
<li>Baptists and Foreign Mission</li>
<li>The Global Spread of the Baptists</li>
<li>Baptist Identity</li>
<li>Conclusion</li>
</ol>
<p>There is certainly plenty of merit for the use of a synthetic approach to historical study, and I’ve benefited immensely from reading other works that follow this approach (in fact, <em>Turning Points</em> by Noll is highly synchronic in some chapters). However, I don’t think a synthetic approach would work well for beginning students who had no general chronological framework into which to plug the disparate concepts a synthetic study would bring to the surface. However, for readers with a general familiarity with the Baptist story, Bebbington’s work may prove a refreshing approach. The synthetic approach is somewhat of a current trend in historiography, but I was encouraged to find that others share my relative antipathy towards it as a practice. For instance, John Aloisi (Assistant Professor of Historical Theology at Detroit Baptist Theological Seminary), gave the following recommendation for this book on <a href="http://dbts.edu/blog/learning-about-the-past-exploring-baptist-history/">his blog</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This book is a very interesting read…. Although described by the publisher as “a chronological survey” (back cover), Bebbington’s work is largely arranged in a topical format that can be be helpful though it also has the potential to be a bit disorienting at times. For example, I found it rather odd to read about William Carey almost 100 pages after Walter Rauschenbusch when Carey was born exactly 100 years before Rauschenbusch. Similarly, the book includes a chapter titled “Women in Baptist Life” (ch. 10). I wondered, why not just discuss key Baptist women at appropriate points in the historical narrative (e.g., in the first nine chapters)? I don’t see a compelling reason for making that topic a distinct chapter. A similar observation could be made about the chapter on religious liberty (ch. 12). On the other hand, if one wants to read an insightful chapter on these topics or on things like Baptists and the social gospel (ch. 8) or Baptists and race relations (ch. 9), Bebbington is a very good place to turn. Overall, Bebbington’s work is definitely helpful and well worth reading, but the potential reader should realize that Bebbington doesn’t tell the story of Baptist history in anything like a chronological narrative. So I’m recommending it with the caveat that if you like to read history in a generally chronological format, Bebbington may drive you crazy. But if you want to read about some key topics in Baptist history, this is a helpful book by a first rate historian.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So anyway, if you’re glazed over with all this rambling about historiography, let me just bring this back to a point of usefulness by sharing Bebbington’s own statements summing up the overall point of the book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“This book attempts to address the question of who Baptists have been over the four centuries of their existence. It tries to take account of ways in which they adapted to the societies in which they lived as well as their central practices. … [I]t must not be assumed that Baptists possessed a single, consistent identity. There were, after all, many types of Baptists. … The variety of Christian bodies called ‘Baptist’ has to be taken into account. So does the consideration that there was great deal of change over time. The circumstances of the early seventeenth century, when Baptists first arose, were very different from those of the early twenty-first century. It was a hallmark of the denomination to be strongly attached to the Bible, but ways of understanding the place of scripture in ordering church life altered over the centuries. Again there was much variation over space.” (p. 2)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“The coverage of this book extends not just over England in the period from 1609 to the present but also over the world at large. … There is, therefore, a need for Baptist history to have an international dimension. Because research on many countries (including some of the nations just mentioned) is at a very preliminary stage, there are all too many gaps in the coverage of the present volume. The aim here is not to deal with every country where Baptists have existed, but to discuss broad trends with representative instances.” (pp. 3-4)</p>
</blockquote>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Rediscovering the Church Fathers by Michael Haykin]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/14/book-review-rediscovering-the-church-fathers-by-michael-haykin/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-14T16:59:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/14/book-review-rediscovering-the-church-fathers-by-michael-haykin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/10/7260060-L.jpg" alt="Rediscovering the Church Fathers" /><figcaption>Rediscovering the Church Fathers</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Haykin, Michael A. G. <em>Rediscovering the Church Fathers: Who They Were and How They Shaped the Church.</em> Wheaton: Crossway, 2011. ISBN 9781433510434. 172 pages. Includes index.</p>
<p>In this book, Haykin combines his remarkable knowledge of the earliest period of church with his zeal for heart-warming devotional Christianity to produce a work that both informs and edifies.</p>
<p>Haykin writes to counter the fact that, in his view, “far too many modern-day evangelicals are either ignorant of or quite uncomfortable with the church fathers” (13). In this regard, he observes, that “<em>certain</em> strains of anti-intellectual fundamentalism have discouraged an interest in that ‘far country’ of church history” (14, my emphasis). He understands that this problem is not entirely due to bad reasons, however, because our “desire to be ‘people of the Book’—an eminently worthy desire—has also led to a lack of interest in other students of Scripture from that earliest period of the church’s history after the apostolic era” (14). Despite this trend, Haykin argues that we should read the church fathers for several reasons. We should read them for “freedom and wisdom,” to understand the New Testament, because of bad press about them, to aid in defending the faith, and for spiritual nurture. In the book, Haykin’s goal is to spark our interest in reading more of the fathers “by looking at several case studies, as it were” (29). These case studies serve to introduce important themes in both the early history of the church and the development of cardinal doctrines. As such, this book is not a comprehensive survey of the fathers, a feature that is apparent by the fact that although there are chapters on many important fathers, some of the most important (like Athanasius and Augustine) are actually left out.</p>
<p>Table of Contents:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Rediscovering the Church Fathers: A Vital Need for Evangelicals</li>
<li>Dying for Christ: The Thought of Ignatius of Antioch</li>
<li>Sharing the Truth: <em>The Letter to Diognetus</em></li>
<li>Interpreting the Scripture: The Exegesis of Origen</li>
<li>Being Kissed: The Eucharistic Piety of Cyprian and Ambrose</li>
<li>Being Holy and Renouncing the World: The Experience of Basil of Caesarea</li>
<li>Saving the Irish: The Mission of Patrick</li>
<li>Walking with the Church Fathers: My First Steps on a Lifelong Journey</li>
</ol>
<p>Appendix 1: Reading the Fathers: A Beginner’s Guide Appendix 2: Reflections on Jaroslav Pelikan, <em>The Emergence of the Catholic Tradition (100–600)</em></p>
<p>I would like to share just a few comments on how some of these chapters impacted me, without going into a summary of each individual chapter or a discussion of major themes that build throughout the book.</p>
<p>Many (if not all) of these chapters nurtured me spiritually. One of Haykin’s many research interests is the study of Christian spirituality, a topic that is the focus of a festschrift in his honor titled <em>The Pure Flame of Devotion: The History of Christian Spirituality</em> (edited by Weaver and Clary). This emphasis shines throughout the book, but I was particularly encouraged by Ignatius’ steadfast anticipation of his own martyrdom and Patrick’s dogged commitment to evangelizing his former captors in western Ireland.</p>
<p>As I expected, many of the chapters deepened my appreciation for the precise formulations of orthodoxy that we enjoy as a result of the diligent efforts forged by these men in times of doctrinal controversy. The chapters on the <em>Letter to Diognetus</em> and Basil of Caesarea were especially helpful in that regard.</p>
<p>On another note, my understanding was transformed by his chapter on Origen. I did not realize it, but I had allowed bad press on the Fathers to distort my understanding of their abilities. I began reading the chapter assuming that Origen’s famous penchant for allegory would mean that there would be little for me to learn about biblical interpretation. But I realized that my understanding of Origen was tinted by a gross misunderstanding. Rather than reading about a half-crazed mystic who simply allowed his imagination to run wild whenever he encountered something he didn’t immediately understand in the biblical text, I learned that Origen was a deeply devoted student of Scripture who understood that allegorical interpretations were not always appropriate (81–82). In fact, Origen actually affirmed three uses for the literal meaning of Scripture, rather than seeing it all as a deeply spiritual parable of something other than what it actually says, and said that the interpreter “should not resort too easily” to allegory (84). Although Origen is perhaps the best-known implementer of the patristic penchant for allegory, he only employed it when he felt it was appropriate, and he articulated principles for the appropriate use of allegory (85–86). Coming away from this chapter, I realized that I have misunderstood the church fathers and their use of allegory because I had not been listening to them. Instead, I had been allowing my own bias (which came from bad press) to keep me from a fair analysis of the facts.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whitefield and the Great Awakening conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/11/whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T16:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/11/whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/10/whitefield-conference.jpg" alt="Whitefield and the Great Awakening" /><figcaption>Whitefield and the Great Awakening</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I am looking forward to attending the annual conference for the Andrew Fuller Center for Baptist Studies this year on “George Whitefield and the Great Awakening.”</p>
<p>Here is the introduction from the <a href="http://events.sbts.edu/andrewfuller/">conference website</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>George Whitefield was not only the most celebrated preacher of the eighteenth century, but he was also a central figure in the creation of modern Evangelicalism. His emphasis on the new birth, his passion for evangelism, his ability to cross denominational boundaries and build networks of Christians based on the gospel and Reformation convictions were central features in what we know today as Evangelicalism. In this conference celebrating the tercentennial (1714) birth of Whitefield, we will explore these key themes of this remarkable Christian’s life and what they meant for his day and mean for ours.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here are the session titles, taken from the <a href="http://www.andrewfullercenter.org/conference/george-whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-october-21-22-2014/">tentative schedule posted on the AFCBS blog</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Session 1: “The Calvinism of George Whitefield” (Thomas S. Kidd)<br />
Session 2: “George Whitefield: Anglican evangelist” (Lee Gatiss)<br />
Session 3: “George Whitefield &amp; the Wesleys” (Stephen Nichols)<br />
Session 4: “Preaching George Whitefield” (Steve Lawson)<br />
Session 5: “The Spirituality of George Whitefield” (Bruce Hindmarsh)<br />
Session 6: “Whitefield’s preaching and the politics of Empire” (Jerome Mahaffey)<br />
Session 7: “The Legacy of George Whitefield” (David Bebbington)<br />
Session 8: “The Hymnody of the Great Awakening” (Esther Crookshank)</p>
</blockquote>
<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/10/tn_9780300181623.jpg" alt="George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father" /><figcaption>George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>As another neat bonus, a few days ago I received my copy of Thomas Kidd’s new biography titled <em>George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father</em> (ISBN 9780300181623). I’m looking forward to digging into this book over the next few days. The hardcover is available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0300181620/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0300181620&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=181623">CBD</a>, and there is also a <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00O56PTU6/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00O56PTU6&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle version</a> available.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
