<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Church History | DuncanJohnson.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/categories/church-history/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-03T09:41:47-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Johnson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Rediscovering the Church Fathers by Michael Haykin]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/14/book-review-rediscovering-the-church-fathers-by-michael-haykin/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-14T16:59:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/14/book-review-rediscovering-the-church-fathers-by-michael-haykin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/10/7260060-L.jpg" alt="Rediscovering the Church Fathers" /><figcaption>Rediscovering the Church Fathers</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Haykin, Michael A. G. <em>Rediscovering the Church Fathers: Who They Were and How They Shaped the Church.</em> Wheaton: Crossway, 2011. ISBN 9781433510434. 172 pages. Includes index.</p>
<p>In this book, Haykin combines his remarkable knowledge of the earliest period of church with his zeal for heart-warming devotional Christianity to produce a work that both informs and edifies.</p>
<p>Haykin writes to counter the fact that, in his view, “far too many modern-day evangelicals are either ignorant of or quite uncomfortable with the church fathers” (13). In this regard, he observes, that “<em>certain</em> strains of anti-intellectual fundamentalism have discouraged an interest in that ‘far country’ of church history” (14, my emphasis). He understands that this problem is not entirely due to bad reasons, however, because our “desire to be ‘people of the Book’—an eminently worthy desire—has also led to a lack of interest in other students of Scripture from that earliest period of the church’s history after the apostolic era” (14). Despite this trend, Haykin argues that we should read the church fathers for several reasons. We should read them for “freedom and wisdom,” to understand the New Testament, because of bad press about them, to aid in defending the faith, and for spiritual nurture. In the book, Haykin’s goal is to spark our interest in reading more of the fathers “by looking at several case studies, as it were” (29). These case studies serve to introduce important themes in both the early history of the church and the development of cardinal doctrines. As such, this book is not a comprehensive survey of the fathers, a feature that is apparent by the fact that although there are chapters on many important fathers, some of the most important (like Athanasius and Augustine) are actually left out.</p>
<p>Table of Contents:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Rediscovering the Church Fathers: A Vital Need for Evangelicals</li>
<li>Dying for Christ: The Thought of Ignatius of Antioch</li>
<li>Sharing the Truth: <em>The Letter to Diognetus</em></li>
<li>Interpreting the Scripture: The Exegesis of Origen</li>
<li>Being Kissed: The Eucharistic Piety of Cyprian and Ambrose</li>
<li>Being Holy and Renouncing the World: The Experience of Basil of Caesarea</li>
<li>Saving the Irish: The Mission of Patrick</li>
<li>Walking with the Church Fathers: My First Steps on a Lifelong Journey</li>
</ol>
<p>Appendix 1: Reading the Fathers: A Beginner’s Guide Appendix 2: Reflections on Jaroslav Pelikan, <em>The Emergence of the Catholic Tradition (100–600)</em></p>
<p>I would like to share just a few comments on how some of these chapters impacted me, without going into a summary of each individual chapter or a discussion of major themes that build throughout the book.</p>
<p>Many (if not all) of these chapters nurtured me spiritually. One of Haykin’s many research interests is the study of Christian spirituality, a topic that is the focus of a festschrift in his honor titled <em>The Pure Flame of Devotion: The History of Christian Spirituality</em> (edited by Weaver and Clary). This emphasis shines throughout the book, but I was particularly encouraged by Ignatius’ steadfast anticipation of his own martyrdom and Patrick’s dogged commitment to evangelizing his former captors in western Ireland.</p>
<p>As I expected, many of the chapters deepened my appreciation for the precise formulations of orthodoxy that we enjoy as a result of the diligent efforts forged by these men in times of doctrinal controversy. The chapters on the <em>Letter to Diognetus</em> and Basil of Caesarea were especially helpful in that regard.</p>
<p>On another note, my understanding was transformed by his chapter on Origen. I did not realize it, but I had allowed bad press on the Fathers to distort my understanding of their abilities. I began reading the chapter assuming that Origen’s famous penchant for allegory would mean that there would be little for me to learn about biblical interpretation. But I realized that my understanding of Origen was tinted by a gross misunderstanding. Rather than reading about a half-crazed mystic who simply allowed his imagination to run wild whenever he encountered something he didn’t immediately understand in the biblical text, I learned that Origen was a deeply devoted student of Scripture who understood that allegorical interpretations were not always appropriate (81–82). In fact, Origen actually affirmed three uses for the literal meaning of Scripture, rather than seeing it all as a deeply spiritual parable of something other than what it actually says, and said that the interpreter “should not resort too easily” to allegory (84). Although Origen is perhaps the best-known implementer of the patristic penchant for allegory, he only employed it when he felt it was appropriate, and he articulated principles for the appropriate use of allegory (85–86). Coming away from this chapter, I realized that I have misunderstood the church fathers and their use of allegory because I had not been listening to them. Instead, I had been allowing my own bias (which came from bad press) to keep me from a fair analysis of the facts.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whitefield and the Great Awakening conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/11/whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T16:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/11/whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/10/whitefield-conference.jpg" alt="Whitefield and the Great Awakening" /><figcaption>Whitefield and the Great Awakening</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I am looking forward to attending the annual conference for the Andrew Fuller Center for Baptist Studies this year on “George Whitefield and the Great Awakening.”</p>
<p>Here is the introduction from the <a href="http://events.sbts.edu/andrewfuller/">conference website</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>George Whitefield was not only the most celebrated preacher of the eighteenth century, but he was also a central figure in the creation of modern Evangelicalism. His emphasis on the new birth, his passion for evangelism, his ability to cross denominational boundaries and build networks of Christians based on the gospel and Reformation convictions were central features in what we know today as Evangelicalism. In this conference celebrating the tercentennial (1714) birth of Whitefield, we will explore these key themes of this remarkable Christian’s life and what they meant for his day and mean for ours.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here are the session titles, taken from the <a href="http://www.andrewfullercenter.org/conference/george-whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-october-21-22-2014/">tentative schedule posted on the AFCBS blog</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Session 1: “The Calvinism of George Whitefield” (Thomas S. Kidd)<br />Session 2: “George Whitefield: Anglican evangelist” (Lee Gatiss)<br />Session 3: “George Whitefield &amp; the Wesleys” (Stephen Nichols)<br />Session 4: “Preaching George Whitefield” (Steve Lawson)<br />Session 5: “The Spirituality of George Whitefield” (Bruce Hindmarsh)<br />Session 6: “Whitefield’s preaching and the politics of Empire” (Jerome Mahaffey)<br />Session 7: “The Legacy of George Whitefield” (David Bebbington)<br />Session 8: “The Hymnody of the Great Awakening” (Esther Crookshank)</p>
</blockquote>
<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/10/tn_9780300181623.jpg" alt="George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father" /><figcaption>George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>As another neat bonus, a few days ago I received my copy of Thomas Kidd’s new biography titled <em>George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father</em> (ISBN 9780300181623). I’m looking forward to digging into this book over the next few days. The hardcover is available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0300181620/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0300181620&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=181623">CBD</a>, and there is also a <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00O56PTU6/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00O56PTU6&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle version</a> available.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Turning Points by Mark Noll]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/09/26/book-review-turning-points-by-mark-noll/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-26T16:19:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/09/26/book-review-turning-points-by-mark-noll</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2013/12/noll.jpg" alt="Turning Points by Mark Noll" /><figcaption>Turning Points by Mark Noll</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Noll, Mark A. <em>Turning Points: Decisive Moments in the History of Christianity.</em> 3rd ed. Grand Rapids: Baker Academic, 2012. ISBN 9780801039966. xii + 356 pages. Includes index.</p>
<p>Available for purchase here:</p>
<ul>
<li>eBook: <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B0085BAEIO/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B0085BAEIO&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon Kindle</a></li>
<li>Paperback: <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=039966">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>This book takes an unusual, and interesting, approach to telling the story of the church by focusing on key turning points throughout the church’s history. Noll describes this approach as “one of the most interesting ways to grasp a general sense of Christian history” (2). The process of identifying these turning points is necessarily subjective, yet he argues that it yields several advantages:</p>
<ul>
<li>“It provides an opportunity to select… and so to bring some order into a massively complicated subject.”</li>
<li>It provides “an opportunity to highlight, to linger over specific moments so as to display the humanity, the complexity, and the uncertainties that constitute the actual history of the church, but that are so often obscured in trying to recount the sweep of centuries.”</li>
<li>It provides “an opportunity to interpret, to state more specifically why certain events, actions, or incidents may have marked an important fork in the road or signaled a new stage in the outworking of Christian history.” (2)</li>
</ul>
<p>The turning points Noll chose can be seen in the table of contents, seen below. <em>[N.B.: The numbers in parentheses for each chapter are dates, not page numbers.]</em></p>
<hr />
<p>Introduction: The Idea of Turning Points and Reasons for Studying the History of Christianity</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Church Pushed Out on Its Own: The Fall of Jerusalem (70)</li>
<li>Realities of Empire: The Council of Nicaea (325)</li>
<li>Doctrine, Politics, and Life in the Word: The Council of Chalcedon (451)</li>
<li>The Monastic Rescue of the Church: Benedict’s <em>Rule</em> (530)</li>
<li>The Culmination of Christendom: The Coronation of Charlemagne (800)</li>
<li>Division between East and West: The Great Schism (1054)</li>
<li>The Beginnings of Protestantism: The Diet of Worms (1521)</li>
<li>A New Europe: The English Act of Supremacy (1534)</li>
<li>Catholic Reform and Worldwide Outreach: The Founding of the Jesuits (1540)</li>
<li>The New Piety: The Conversion of the Wesleys (1738)</li>
<li>Discontents of the Modern West: The French Revolution (1789)</li>
<li>A Faith for All the World: The Edinburgh Missionary Conference (1910)</li>
<li>Mobilizing for the Future: The Second Vatican Council (1962–65) and the Lausanne Congress on World Evangelization (1974)</li>
</ol>
<p>Afterword: The Character of Christianity and the Search for Turning Points</p>
<hr />
<p>Noll emphasizes that “the fourteen turning points singled out for special attention … are by no means the only ones that could have been selected” (3). He explains that the process of selection itself is an important and useful exercise, and notes that “if the book inspires others to think about why the turning points found here are not as important as other possibilities, it will have been a successful book” (4). He then briefly outlines the structure of each chapter, noting that he always begins with “a relatively detailed account of the turning point itself” followed by more theoretical discussions of “why, how, and so what” (4). Additionally, each chapter features a hymn and a prayer from the general time period of the chapter as well as several longer quotations from people involved in the events of the chapter.</p>
<p>After explaining the structure and nature of the book, Noll takes up a larger question: why be concerned about church history at all? Noll offers several reasons why the study of church history is valuable.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>“Studying the history of Christianity provides repeated, concrete demonstration concerning the irreducibly historical character of the Christian faith” (5).</li>
<li>It “provide[s] perspective on the interpretation of Scripture” (6).</li>
<li>“The study of church history is also useful as a laboratory for examining Christian interactions with surrounding culture” (7).</li>
<li>Because “God sustains the church despite the church’s own frequent efforts to betray its Savior and its own high calling, … study of the past can be useful … in shaping proper Christian attitudes” (8).</li>
</ol>
<p>In the introduction, Noll mentions a few of his own convictions which influence his portrayal of the events of church history. He generally prefers the term “history of Christianity” over “church history,” partly because he believes that “‘Christianity’ means something definite with boundaries that are fairly well defined by the major creeds.” Beyond that, Noll writes with “evangelical Protestant convictions” that “lead [him] to think that revitalized forms of Reformation faith are the truest and best forms of Christianity” (9–10). Noll qualifies this belief, however, with the observation that “historical study has convinced me that confessional Protestants have sometimes honored the ideals of the Reformation more in words than in reality. Historical study also shows that believers in other Christian traditions regularly display Christlike virtues and practice humble dependence upon God’s grace more than my confessional Protestant convictions tell me they should.” As a result, he has “tried to write with as much respect as possible for the widely diverse forms of Christianity that have been practiced with integrity, and continue to be practiced with integrity, in all parts of the Christian church” (10).</p>
<p>Of course, Noll’s statements regarding Catholicism reflect his perspective as an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evangelicals_and_Catholics_Together#Endorsed_By">endorser of <em>Evangelicals and Catholics Together</em> in 1994</a>. I think it is useful to read authors from outside my own tradition, but that does not obviate the need to read with discernment.</p>
<p>Noll’s book is helpful for a number of different reasons.</p>
<ul>
<li>By approaching the history of Christianity from the vantage point of key turning points, he provides an interesting and unusual perspective. This also enables the chapters to stand on their own while still making sense to a reader who reads the book through from beginning to end.</li>
<li>Noll’s writing style is simultaneously lucid and dense. He is capable of drawing complex connections between seemingly unrelated events, yet throughout the process his ideas remain incredibly clear. My students all said that they enjoyed his writing, but that he always forced them to think carefully.</li>
<li><p>Over the course of the book, he develops several key ideas into recurring themes. One example appears in Chapter 1, where he argues that the fall of Jerusalem created a new problem for the Christian church. Suddenly severed from any connection to its Jewish roots, the church was forced to emerge as an independent entity while maintaining a connection to its apostolic roots. The need to establish <em>apostolicity</em> could be resolved in three different ways: by appealing to the authority of the New Testament canon, by appealing to the authority of the emerging episcopacy, or by appealing to the authority of the apostolic creeds. What is interesting about these three distinct sources of stability is that Protestants, Roman Catholics, and the Orthodox each tend to place more emphasis on one of those three, as displayed in the chart below:</p>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 25%" />
<col style="width: 30%" />
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Tradition</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Stabilizing Element</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Protestants</p></td>
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Canon</p></td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Roman Catholics</p></td>
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Episcopacy</p></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Orthodox</p></td>
<td style="text-align: left;"><p>Creed</p></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>As the history of the church progresses through time, Noll quite effectively shows how these three contrasting sources of authority shape future conflicts within the church.</p>
<p>Another example of a recurring theme throughout the book is the concept of <em>Christendom,</em> the idea which began to develop in the post-Roman European world that Christ’s kingdom extended to a specific geographical location (Europe), and that thus church and state ought to be deeply entwined. The idea of Christendom appears to climax in the coronation of Charlemagne, and much of the spiritual and political energy of the Medieval period is wrapped up in preserving that (un)holy (un)Roman (un)Empire.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Although each chapter is interesting and carefully researched, it does become evident that some chapters play more to Noll’s strengths than others. From time to time, he indicates in a footnote that he is depending upon another secondary source for much of his material in a chapter. In other chapters where the subject material is within an area where he has done extensive research, he writes with considerably more freedom as he draws upon his own extensive knowledge. An example of one of his stronger chapters is chapter 10 on the Evangelical Revival under the Wesleys (his name appears twice in the “Further Reading” section at the end of the chapter), and an example of one of his weaker chapters is chapter 9 on the Jesuits. Still, his skills as a researcher shine throughout, and there is a remarkable uniformity of quality throughout.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Readings in Baptist History: Four Centuries of Selected Documents by Joe Early]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/02/12/book-review-readings-in-baptist-history-four-centuries-of-selected-documents-by-joe-early/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-12T13:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/02/12/book-review-readings-in-baptist-history-four-centuries-of-selected-documents-by-joe-early</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/02/early.jpg" alt="Readings in Baptist History by Joe Early" /><figcaption>Readings in Baptist History by Joe Early</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Early, Joseph. <em>Readings in Baptist History: Four Centuries of Selected Documents.</em> Nashville, TN: B&amp;H Academic, 2008. ISBN 9780805446746. 288 pages.</p>
<p>Available for purchase from:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=446746">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0805446745/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0805446745&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca (Canada)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0805446745/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0805446745&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20">Amazon.com (USA)</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>By necessity, the study of history requires the perusal of historic texts. By devoting attention to primary sources, the student learns from the perspective of eyewitnesses and participants. Sometimes reading primary sources uncovers the student’s own bias; at other times it presents the biases of the original actors in their own context. In studying any historical period or genre, beginning students oftentimes ignore important primary sources, not necessarily from lack of interest, but because those texts are scattered in various locations. A common remedy for this problem is a sourcebook, a published edition of key primary sources on a given topic. Joseph Early’s <em>Readings in Baptist History</em> provides an up-to-date sourcebook of key Baptist texts in one affordable volume.</p>
<p>This work fills a largely overlooked niche in the literature on Baptist history. In his preface, Early observes that although several books on Baptist history have appeared since H. Leon McBeth’s <em>Baptist Heritage: Four Centuries of Baptist Witness</em> in 1987, no new sourcebook has been produced since the 1990 release of McBeth’s companion volume, <em>A Sourcebook for Baptist Heritage.</em> In this work, Early adds newer documents while also including “seminal older documents” (v) to provide a comprehensive update.</p>
<p>In selecting texts for inclusion, Early seeks “to provide as broad a scope and be as inclusive as possible” (vi). As a result, representative texts from a variety of Baptist traditions appear within the collection, including “British Baptists, Black Baptists, American Baptists, Southern Baptists, Russian Baptists, Landmark Baptists, and Fundamental Baptists” (vi). Of course, selecting key texts to include means that some texts must be excluded, and Early notes that his selections were limited by word count and the interests of his intended audience of “students of Baptist history” (vi).</p>
<p>The selections in the book are organized chronologically, beginning with texts from the exiled English General Baptists led by John Smyth and Thomas Helwys in 1609. The book exhibits a generally even distribution of texts over the course of Baptist history, with seven chapters from the seventeenth century, eight from the eighteenth century, twelve from the nineteenth century, and fourteen from the twentieth century. A complete chapter listing is included below this review for those interested in the details.</p>
<p>One editorial decision is unfortunate, though based on admirable motives. In the interest of appealing to a broad readership, there are no editorial introductions to the various texts included in the work. Early indicates that he chose not to include comments on individual texts so that he would not “color the interpretation of the documents” (vi). Unfortunately, this means that students sometimes struggle to understand the significance and place of the documents within the broader context of Baptist history.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most significant contribution of the book is that it includes documents relevant to the theological controversy within the Southern Baptist Convention. In the chapter that includes the Baptist Faith and Message, the three different versions (1925, 1963, 2000) are presented in three parallel columns for easy comparison.</p>
<p>My own students reacted to the book quite positively, although at first they seemed unexcited by the prospect of reading a collection of source texts. As their background knowledge of the Baptist story developed over the semester, they became more interested in the readings. By the end of the semester, some of my students were saying that they enjoyed reading Early even more than their other textbook.</p>
<p>For a bibliography of supplemental readings, see <a href="http://www.baptisttheology.org/book-reviews/readings-in-baptist-history">the review by Jason G. Duesing of Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
<!-- more -->
<hr />
<p><em>List of Chapters</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Character of the Beast, 1609</li>
<li>Letter to Sir William Hammerton, 1609</li>
<li>A Declaration of Faith of English People Remaining in Amsterdam in Holland, 1611</li>
<li>A Short Declaration of the Mystery of Iniquity, 1612</li>
<li>The Beginnings of the Particular Baptists and the Birth of Immersion, 1633</li>
<li>The Bloudy Tennent of Persecution, 1644</li>
<li>The Whipping of Obadiah Holmes, 1651</li>
<li>The Power of the Association, 1749</li>
<li>The Birth of the Charleston Association, 1751</li>
<li>Birth of the Sandy Creek Baptist Association, 1758</li>
<li>A Body of Doctrinal and Practical Divinity, 1769</li>
<li>An Appeal to the Public for Religious Liberty, 1773</li>
<li>Black Baptists</li>
<li>The Rights of Conscience Inalienable, 1791</li>
<li>An Enquiry, 1792</li>
<li>The “Wall of Separation”</li>
<li>Formation of the English Baptist Union, 1813</li>
<li>Address at the Formation of the Triennial Convention, 1814</li>
<li>Treatise on Slavery, 1822</li>
<li>Primitivism and the Antimission Movement</li>
<li>Report and Warning about Campbellism, 1830</li>
<li>The Georgia Test Case and the Alabama Resolutions</li>
<li>Southern and Northern Perspectives on the 1845 Schism</li>
<li>Address Explaining Why the Southern Baptist Convention was Organized, 1845</li>
<li>Old Landmarkism: What is It?</li>
<li>A Letter from China</li>
<li>Another Word Concerning the Down-Grade</li>
<li>The Baptist World Alliance</li>
<li>The Kingdom of God, 1917</li>
<li>Baptists and Religious Liberty, 1920</li>
<li>The Impact of J. Frank Norris on Baptist Life</li>
<li>The Cooperative Program, 1924</li>
<li>The Trail of Blood, 1931</li>
<li>The Baptist Way, 1945</li>
<li>Russian Baptist History from 1929 to 1963, 1967</li>
<li>Origins of the Conservative Resurgence</li>
<li>The Resurgence of Calvinism</li>
<li>Peace Committee Report, 1987</li>
<li>Doctrinal Statement of the Baptist Missionary Association of America, 1989</li>
<li>The Cooperative Baptist Fellowship</li>
<li>The Baptist Faith and Message, 1925, 1963, 2000</li>
</ol>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Baptist Ways: A History by Bill Leonard]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/01/16/book-review-baptist-ways-a-history-by-bill-leonard/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/01/16/book-review-baptist-ways-a-history-by-bill-leonard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/01/leonard.jpg" alt="Baptist Ways by Bill Leonard" /><figcaption>Baptist Ways by Bill Leonard</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Leonard, Bill J. <em>Baptist Ways: A History.</em> Valley Forge, PA: Judson Press, 2003. ISBN 9780817012311. xiv + 464 pages.</p>
<p>Available for purchase from:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=012311">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0817012311/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0817012311&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca (Canada)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0817012311/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0817012311&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20">Amazon.com (USA)</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>Conceived as a replacement for Robert Torbet’s well-known text, <em>A History of the Baptists</em>, this book attempts to survey the worldwide history of Baptists from their origins in seventeeth-century England. Leonard states his thesis clearly in the opening paragraph of his preface:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The thesis of this book is relatively simple. It suggests that amid certain distinctives, Baptist identity is configured in a variety of ways by groups, subgroups, and individuals who claim the Baptist name. This identity extends across a theological spectrum from Arminian to Calvinist, from conservative to liberal, from open to closed communionist, and from denominationalist to independent.” (xi)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This thesis allows Leonard to include a broad survey of individuals and groups, including giving significant attention to the role of women and minorities in the history of the Baptists. One interesting feature is regular description of Baptist hymnody and worship. Throughout the work, Leonard draws primarily from secondary sources, although the notes (which are placed as endnotes after each chapter) indicate a measured use of primary sources.</p>
<p>The book alternates between chronological and geographical perspectives. Chapter 1 provides a standard introduction to the study of Baptist history, surveying common doctrinal distinctives and contrasting the three views of Baptist origins. Chapters 2–9 proceed chronologically, telling the story of English and American Baptists from their obscure seventeenth-century beginnings to national prominence during the nineteenth-century. Chapters 10–14 survey the Baptist movement elsewhere, giving the book a global scope. For instance, chapter 10 provides a concise summary of Baptists in Canada (227–244), followed by brief sections on Baptist efforts in various Latin American countries. These chapters will be of most interest to readers outside the United States, but are important for all readers to provide a full understanding of the various kinds of Baptists to be found throughout the world. Chapters 15 and 16 resume the story of Baptists in the West during the twentieth century.</p>
<p><em>Chapters</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Baptist Ways: Defining a People</li>
<li>Baptist Beginnings: The Historical Context</li>
<li>English Baptists: The Seventeenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: Beginnings</li>
<li>English Baptists: The Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: The Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in Britain: The Nineteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: 1800-1845</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: 1845-1900</li>
<li>Baptists in the Americas and the Caribbean</li>
<li>African American Baptists</li>
<li>Baptists in Greater Britain</li>
<li>Baptists in Europe</li>
<li>Baptists in Africa and Asia</li>
<li>Baptists in the British Isles and Europe: The Twentieth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: The Twentieth Century</li>
</ol>
<!-- Omit following paragraph... not sure I have the right examples, although I know I felt this way at various points in the book. Too bad I didn't mark it. -->
<!-- Due to the broad scope of the book, Leonard frequently mentions names and events without remarking on their significance. Examples of this include his mention of Benoi Stinson (211--212) and James Manning (231). Without  -->
<p>Predictably, the book reflects the denominational affiliation of its publisher, Judson Press. As the <a href="http://www.judsonpress.com/home_about_us.cfm">publishing arm of the American Baptist Churches USA</a>, Judson Press represents a particular constituency of Baptists. The book puts some emphasis on this strain of Baptist identity, tracing the development of the ABCUSA out of the Northern Baptist Convention in some detail in chapter 16.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the book omits or downplays some important events in Southern Baptist history. For instance, the extensive controversy over the modernism of Crawford H. Toy receives no treatment. Toy, though he was professor at The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary from 1869–1879, is only mentioned as a missionary appointee to Japan who “never went because the [Foreign Mission Board] delayed all appointments in anticipation of the Civil War and related economic difficulties” (353). The dates of his professorship at Southern appear only in an otherwise unremarkable parenthesis, and there is no mention of his broken engagement to missionary Lottie Moon. As <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/30149574">other reviewers</a> <a href="http://www.baptisttheology.org/book-reviews/baptist-ways-a-history/">have noted</a>, the Conservative Resurgence in the SBC also receives scant coverage, appearing only in summary on pages 414–415.</p>
<p>Occasionally, the book suggests that an emphasis on biblical literalism results in erratic or erroneous conclusions. An early example of this pattern occurs in the treatment of John Smyth, the early sixteenth-century Baptist. Smyth was certainly unstable, following a spiritual trajectory that parallels that of Roger Williams in America. Smyth began as an Anglican until he adopted Separatist views. Later, he founded the General Baptists along with Thomas Helwys by baptizing himself and then his own followers. This self-baptism brought criticism, and eventually Smyth repudiated his own baptism and sought admission into a nearby Mennonite sect. The book attributes Smyth’s restlessness to his commitment to the Bible: “His biblicism took him through many Protestant communities in a search for the fullest revelation available” (25). Smyth was undoubtedly a biblicist, but there are other explanations for his repudiation of his self-baptism. On occasion, the book suggests that biblicism leads to other negative results, which will disappoint conservative readers.</p>
<p>Other reviews have been mixed in their final appraisal of Leonard’s text, despite the unanimous acknowledgement that producing a one-volume Baptist history is a difficult task. As a potential course textbook, the work suffers from a lack of visual aids (a deficiency that equally applies to the competing volumes by Torbet and McBeth). Other complaints include the slightly negative treatment of more conservative Baptist traditions and the deliberately international focus of chapters 10–16. On the other hand, these two complaints illustrate and, to some degree, substantiate Leonard’s thesis that Baptists are a broadly differentiated sect. As a potential textbook for a course on Baptist history, I find Leonard’s text to be useful despite these perceived weaknesses. This is especially true for me as I teach the history of the Baptists outside of the United States of America. Although Leonard’s book should not be the only volume that students of the Baptists consult, I am convinced that it is a worthy member of the body of literature on the topic.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
