<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Conferences | DuncanJohnson.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/categories/conferences/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/"/>
  <updated>2016-11-04T20:31:36-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Johnson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reformation Conference in Calgary]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2016/10/08/reformation-conference-in-calgary/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-08T20:48:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2016/10/08/reformation-conference-in-calgary</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="http://duncanjohnson.ca/images/2016/10/luther.jpg" title="Luther at the Diet of Worms" alt="Luther at the Diet of Worms" /><figcaption>Luther at the Diet of Worms</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Next week I’ll be speaking about the Protestant Reformation at <a href="http://foundationbaptistchurch.com/">Foundation Baptist Church</a> in Calgary. Below is some promotional information about the sessions. More information will be available on the <a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/calgary-reformation-conference/">conference website</a>, where you can sign up for email updates.</p>
<p>Nearly 500 years ago, the events of the Protestant Reformation upended the western world. Our pursuit of God today is greatly helped by the rediscoveries of the Reformers. Because our doctrine depends on the discoveries of faithful men and women in the past, we need to know our family history. Come to our Fall Conference on the Reformation for an encouraging and edifying look at what those turbulent times of the past mean for us today. <!-- more --></p>
<p><strong>Sessions</strong></p>
<p>The Wednesday session and the Sunday session will be held at the Braeside Community Centre (11024 Braeside Dr. SW). The Thursday, Friday, and Saturday sessions will meet at a church member’s home. Please call the church office for directions (403-251-5920).</p>
<table style="width:98%;">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 14%" />
<col style="width: 83%" />
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Wed, Oct 12<br />
(7–8 PM)</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">An Entire Life of Repentance: The Need for Reformation</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Thu, Oct 13<br />
(7–9 PM)</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">“The Just Shall Live by Faith”: Martin Luther and Salvation by Faith Alone</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Fri, Oct 14<br />
(7–9 PM)</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">“This Do in Remembrance of Me”: Huldrych Zwingli and the Lord’s Supper</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Sat, Oct 15<br />
(10 AM)</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">“What God has Joined, Let No One Separate”: John Calvin and the Doctrine of the Church</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Sun, Oct 16<br />
(10 AM)</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Always Reforming: The Ongoing Significance of Reformation</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Speaker</strong></p>
<p>Duncan Johnson (M.Div., Bob Jones University, 2011) teaches courses on Bible, theology, and church history at Foundation Baptist College in Edmonton. One of his passions is to show believers today how their faith connects through past generations with the apostolic teachings of the Scripture itself.</p>
<p>Image credit: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:%D0%9B%D1%8E%D1%82%D0%B5%D1%80_%D0%B2_%D0%92%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%BC%D1%81%D0%B5.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Whitefield and the Great Awakening conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/11/whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-11T16:01:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/10/11/whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/10/whitefield-conference.jpg" alt="Whitefield and the Great Awakening" /><figcaption>Whitefield and the Great Awakening</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I am looking forward to attending the annual conference for the Andrew Fuller Center for Baptist Studies this year on “George Whitefield and the Great Awakening.”</p>
<p>Here is the introduction from the <a href="http://events.sbts.edu/andrewfuller/">conference website</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>George Whitefield was not only the most celebrated preacher of the eighteenth century, but he was also a central figure in the creation of modern Evangelicalism. His emphasis on the new birth, his passion for evangelism, his ability to cross denominational boundaries and build networks of Christians based on the gospel and Reformation convictions were central features in what we know today as Evangelicalism. In this conference celebrating the tercentennial (1714) birth of Whitefield, we will explore these key themes of this remarkable Christian’s life and what they meant for his day and mean for ours.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here are the session titles, taken from the <a href="http://www.andrewfullercenter.org/conference/george-whitefield-and-the-great-awakening-october-21-22-2014/">tentative schedule posted on the AFCBS blog</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Session 1: “The Calvinism of George Whitefield” (Thomas S. Kidd)<br />
Session 2: “George Whitefield: Anglican evangelist” (Lee Gatiss)<br />
Session 3: “George Whitefield &amp; the Wesleys” (Stephen Nichols)<br />
Session 4: “Preaching George Whitefield” (Steve Lawson)<br />
Session 5: “The Spirituality of George Whitefield” (Bruce Hindmarsh)<br />
Session 6: “Whitefield’s preaching and the politics of Empire” (Jerome Mahaffey)<br />
Session 7: “The Legacy of George Whitefield” (David Bebbington)<br />
Session 8: “The Hymnody of the Great Awakening” (Esther Crookshank)</p>
</blockquote>
<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/10/tn_9780300181623.jpg" alt="George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father" /><figcaption>George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>As another neat bonus, a few days ago I received my copy of Thomas Kidd’s new biography titled <em>George Whitefield: America’s Spiritual Founding Father</em> (ISBN 9780300181623). I’m looking forward to digging into this book over the next few days. The hardcover is available from <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0300181620/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0300181620&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon</a> and <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=181623">CBD</a>, and there is also a <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00O56PTU6/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00O56PTU6&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Kindle version</a> available.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
