<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Preaching | DuncanJohnson.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/categories/preaching/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-04T17:02:20-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Johnson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Man's Wisdom vs. God's Wisdom]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/05/25/mans-wisdom-vs-gods-wisdom/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-25T08:09:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/05/25/mans-wisdom-vs-gods-wisdom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every now and then, you hear somebody preach a sermon that really sticks in your memory. For me, this happened when I heard <a href="http://www.sermonaudio.com/sermoninfo.asp?SID=32111153492">this sermon</a> by Brent Cook in chapel at Bob Jones University. The message takes 1 Cor. 1:18 as its foundational text:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For the message of the cross is foolishness to those who are perishing, but to us who are being saved it is the power of God. (1 Corinthians 1:18 NKJ)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I replayed this sermon for my students in my class on evangelism a year later (the link above goes to the website for that course), and I’ve listened to this message many times since. It came to mind again today as I was studying 2 Cor. 2:12–3:18.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ryle on Preaching Simply]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/05/17/ryle-on-preaching-simply/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-17T22:13:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/05/17/ryle-on-preaching-simply</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/05/ryle.jpg" title="J. C. Ryle" alt="J. C. Ryle" /><figcaption>J. C. Ryle</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I just read a little booklet by J. C. Ryle. Titled <em>Simplicity in Preaching: A Few Short Hints on a Great Subject</em>, the book contains a lecture Ryle delivered in 1882 and spans 48 tiny pages (each page includes only a couple paragraphs). I suspect that the entire thing would work today as a lengthy blog post.</p>
<p>Much of what Ryle says is helpful, though some of it reflects the prevailing ideas of his times and is less useful now (e.g., his ambivalence towards the use of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linguistic_purism_in_English">“Saxon words” in English</a>). Though I recommend you <a href="http://books.google.ca/books/about/Simplicity_in_preaching_a_few_short_hint.html?id=MgkDAAAAQAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y">read the whole thing</a>, here are five directives Ryle gives to those who would attain simplicity in preaching:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Have a clear knowledge of what you are going to preach.</li>
<li>Use simple words.</li>
<li>Seek to acquire a simple style of composition, with short sentences and as few colons and semi-colons as possible.</li>
<li>Aim at directness.</li>
<li>Make abundant use of illustration and anecdote.</li>
</ol>
<p>HT: <a href="https://twitter.com/steveweaver/status/467830530336382977">Steve Weaver</a><br />
Image credit: By Kowalker [CC-BY-SA-3.0 (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0)], via <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:J_C_Ryle.jpg">Wikimedia Commons</a></p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
