<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Books | DuncanJohnson.ca]]></title>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-22T12:38:21-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Duncan Johnson]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Block class on John's Epistles]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/03/10/block-class-on-johns-epistles/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T10:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/03/10/block-class-on-johns-epistles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ll be teaching a block class on John’s letters this coming April 28–May 3. I thought I’d share the book for this class (as well as some general information) below. More details (including the syllabus and assignment list) will be forthcoming soon on the <a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/ex315-2014/">course website</a>.</p>
<p><em>Description:</em> An exposition of 1, 2, and 3 John, with an emphasis on John’s theology.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/03/tn_9780802825186.jpg" alt="The Epistles of John" /><figcaption>The Epistles of John</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><em>Textbook:</em> Marshall, I. Howard. <em>The Epistles of John.</em> New International Commentary on the New Testament. Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans, 2001. ISBN 9780802825186.</p>
<p>Available for purchase here:</p>
<ul>
<li>eBook: <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B0028Y4AYS/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B0028Y4AYS&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon Kindle</a><br /> (<em>Note:</em> I wouldn’t recommend getting a technical commentary like this on Kindle, but this is a matter of preference.)</li>
<li>Hardcover:
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0802825184/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0802825184&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=2189">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Readings in Baptist History: Four Centuries of Selected Documents by Joe Early]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/02/12/book-review-readings-in-baptist-history-four-centuries-of-selected-documents-by-joe-early/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-12T13:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/02/12/book-review-readings-in-baptist-history-four-centuries-of-selected-documents-by-joe-early</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/02/early.jpg" alt="Readings in Baptist History by Joe Early" /><figcaption>Readings in Baptist History by Joe Early</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Early, Joseph. <em>Readings in Baptist History: Four Centuries of Selected Documents.</em> Nashville, TN: B&amp;H Academic, 2008. ISBN 9780805446746. 288 pages.</p>
<p>Available for purchase from:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=446746">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0805446745/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0805446745&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca (Canada)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0805446745/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0805446745&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20">Amazon.com (USA)</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>By necessity, the study of history requires the perusal of historic texts. By devoting attention to primary sources, the student learns from the perspective of eyewitnesses and participants. Sometimes reading primary sources uncovers the student’s own bias; at other times it presents the biases of the original actors in their own context. In studying any historical period or genre, beginning students oftentimes ignore important primary sources, not necessarily from lack of interest, but because those texts are scattered in various locations. A common remedy for this problem is a sourcebook, a published edition of key primary sources on a given topic. Joseph Early’s <em>Readings in Baptist History</em> provides an up-to-date sourcebook of key Baptist texts in one affordable volume.</p>
<p>This work fills a largely overlooked niche in the literature on Baptist history. In his preface, Early observes that although several books on Baptist history have appeared since H. Leon McBeth’s <em>Baptist Heritage: Four Centuries of Baptist Witness</em> in 1987, no new sourcebook has been produced since the 1990 release of McBeth’s companion volume, <em>A Sourcebook for Baptist Heritage.</em> In this work, Early adds newer documents while also including “seminal older documents” (v) to provide a comprehensive update.</p>
<p>In selecting texts for inclusion, Early seeks “to provide as broad a scope and be as inclusive as possible” (vi). As a result, representative texts from a variety of Baptist traditions appear within the collection, including “British Baptists, Black Baptists, American Baptists, Southern Baptists, Russian Baptists, Landmark Baptists, and Fundamental Baptists” (vi). Of course, selecting key texts to include means that some texts must be excluded, and Early notes that his selections were limited by word count and the interests of his intended audience of “students of Baptist history” (vi).</p>
<p>The selections in the book are organized chronologically, beginning with texts from the exiled English General Baptists led by John Smyth and Thomas Helwys in 1609. The book exhibits a generally even distribution of texts over the course of Baptist history, with seven chapters from the seventeenth century, eight from the eighteenth century, twelve from the nineteenth century, and fourteen from the twentieth century. A complete chapter listing is included below this review for those interested in the details.</p>
<p>One editorial decision is unfortunate, though based on admirable motives. In the interest of appealing to a broad readership, there are no editorial introductions to the various texts included in the work. Early indicates that he chose not to include comments on individual texts so that he would not “color the interpretation of the documents” (vi). Unfortunately, this means that students sometimes struggle to understand the significance and place of the documents within the broader context of Baptist history.</p>
<p>Perhaps the most significant contribution of the book is that it includes documents relevant to the theological controversy within the Southern Baptist Convention. In the chapter that includes the Baptist Faith and Message, the three different versions (1925, 1963, 2000) are presented in three parallel columns for easy comparison.</p>
<p>My own students reacted to the book quite positively, although at first they seemed unexcited by the prospect of reading a collection of source texts. As their background knowledge of the Baptist story developed over the semester, they became more interested in the readings. By the end of the semester, some of my students were saying that they enjoyed reading Early even more than their other textbook.</p>
<p>For a bibliography of supplemental readings, see <a href="http://www.baptisttheology.org/book-reviews/readings-in-baptist-history">the review by Jason G. Duesing of Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary</a>.</p>
<!-- more -->

<hr />
<p><em>List of Chapters</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The Character of the Beast, 1609</li>
<li>Letter to Sir William Hammerton, 1609</li>
<li>A Declaration of Faith of English People Remaining in Amsterdam in Holland, 1611</li>
<li>A Short Declaration of the Mystery of Iniquity, 1612</li>
<li>The Beginnings of the Particular Baptists and the Birth of Immersion, 1633</li>
<li>The Bloudy Tennent of Persecution, 1644</li>
<li>The Whipping of Obadiah Holmes, 1651</li>
<li>The Power of the Association, 1749</li>
<li>The Birth of the Charleston Association, 1751</li>
<li>Birth of the Sandy Creek Baptist Association, 1758</li>
<li>A Body of Doctrinal and Practical Divinity, 1769</li>
<li>An Appeal to the Public for Religious Liberty, 1773</li>
<li>Black Baptists</li>
<li>The Rights of Conscience Inalienable, 1791</li>
<li>An Enquiry, 1792</li>
<li>The “Wall of Separation”</li>
<li>Formation of the English Baptist Union, 1813</li>
<li>Address at the Formation of the Triennial Convention, 1814</li>
<li>Treatise on Slavery, 1822</li>
<li>Primitivism and the Antimission Movement</li>
<li>Report and Warning about Campbellism, 1830</li>
<li>The Georgia Test Case and the Alabama Resolutions</li>
<li>Southern and Northern Perspectives on the 1845 Schism</li>
<li>Address Explaining Why the Southern Baptist Convention was Organized, 1845</li>
<li>Old Landmarkism: What is It?</li>
<li>A Letter from China</li>
<li>Another Word Concerning the Down-Grade</li>
<li>The Baptist World Alliance</li>
<li>The Kingdom of God, 1917</li>
<li>Baptists and Religious Liberty, 1920</li>
<li>The Impact of J. Frank Norris on Baptist Life</li>
<li>The Cooperative Program, 1924</li>
<li>The Trail of Blood, 1931</li>
<li>The Baptist Way, 1945</li>
<li>Russian Baptist History from 1929 to 1963, 1967</li>
<li>Origins of the Conservative Resurgence</li>
<li>The Resurgence of Calvinism</li>
<li>Peace Committee Report, 1987</li>
<li>Doctrinal Statement of the Baptist Missionary Association of America, 1989</li>
<li>The Cooperative Baptist Fellowship</li>
<li>The Baptist Faith and Message, 1925, 1963, 2000</li>
</ol>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Review - Baptist Ways: A History by Bill Leonard]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/01/16/book-review-baptist-ways-a-history-by-bill-leonard/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-16T11:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2014/01/16/book-review-baptist-ways-a-history-by-bill-leonard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img src="/images/2014/01/leonard.jpg" alt="Baptist Ways by Bill Leonard" /><figcaption>Baptist Ways by Bill Leonard</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Leonard, Bill J. <em>Baptist Ways: A History.</em> Valley Forge, PA: Judson Press, 2003. ISBN 9780817012311. xiv + 464 pages.</p>
<p>Available for purchase from:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=012311">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0817012311/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=0817012311&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon.ca (Canada)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0817012311/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0817012311&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanandmego-20">Amazon.com (USA)</a></li>
</ul>
<hr />
<p>Conceived as a replacement for Robert Torbet’s well-known text, <em>A History of the Baptists</em>, this book attempts to survey the worldwide history of Baptists from their origins in seventeeth-century England. Leonard states his thesis clearly in the opening paragraph of his preface:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The thesis of this book is relatively simple. It suggests that amid certain distinctives, Baptist identity is configured in a variety of ways by groups, subgroups, and individuals who claim the Baptist name. This identity extends across a theological spectrum from Arminian to Calvinist, from conservative to liberal, from open to closed communionist, and from denominationalist to independent.” (xi)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This thesis allows Leonard to include a broad survey of individuals and groups, including giving significant attention to the role of women and minorities in the history of the Baptists. One interesting feature is regular description of Baptist hymnody and worship. Throughout the work, Leonard draws primarily from secondary sources, although the notes (which are placed as endnotes after each chapter) indicate a measured use of primary sources.</p>
<p>The book alternates between chronological and geographical perspectives. Chapter 1 provides a standard introduction to the study of Baptist history, surveying common doctrinal distinctives and contrasting the three views of Baptist origins. Chapters 2–9 proceed chronologically, telling the story of English and American Baptists from their obscure seventeenth-century beginnings to national prominence during the nineteenth-century. Chapters 10–14 survey the Baptist movement elsewhere, giving the book a global scope. For instance, chapter 10 provides a concise summary of Baptists in Canada (227–244), followed by brief sections on Baptist efforts in various Latin American countries. These chapters will be of most interest to readers outside the United States, but are important for all readers to provide a full understanding of the various kinds of Baptists to be found throughout the world. Chapters 15 and 16 resume the story of Baptists in the West during the twentieth century.</p>
<p><em>Chapters</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Baptist Ways: Defining a People</li>
<li>Baptist Beginnings: The Historical Context</li>
<li>English Baptists: The Seventeenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: Beginnings</li>
<li>English Baptists: The Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: The Eighteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in Britain: The Nineteenth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: 1800-1845</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: 1845-1900</li>
<li>Baptists in the Americas and the Caribbean</li>
<li>African American Baptists</li>
<li>Baptists in Greater Britain</li>
<li>Baptists in Europe</li>
<li>Baptists in Africa and Asia</li>
<li>Baptists in the British Isles and Europe: The Twentieth Century</li>
<li>Baptists in the United States: The Twentieth Century</li>
</ol>
<!-- Omit following paragraph... not sure I have the right examples, although I know I felt this way at various points in the book. Too bad I didn't mark it. -->
<!-- Due to the broad scope of the book, Leonard frequently mentions names and events without remarking on their significance. Examples of this include his mention of Benoi Stinson (211--212) and James Manning (231). Without  -->

<p>Predictably, the book reflects the denominational affiliation of its publisher, Judson Press. As the <a href="http://www.judsonpress.com/home_about_us.cfm">publishing arm of the American Baptist Churches USA</a>, Judson Press represents a particular constituency of Baptists. The book puts some emphasis on this strain of Baptist identity, tracing the development of the ABCUSA out of the Northern Baptist Convention in some detail in chapter 16.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the book omits or downplays some important events in Southern Baptist history. For instance, the extensive controversy over the modernism of Crawford H. Toy receives no treatment. Toy, though he was professor at The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary from 1869–1879, is only mentioned as a missionary appointee to Japan who “never went because the [Foreign Mission Board] delayed all appointments in anticipation of the Civil War and related economic difficulties” (353). The dates of his professorship at Southern appear only in an otherwise unremarkable parenthesis, and there is no mention of his broken engagement to missionary Lottie Moon. As <a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/30149574">other reviewers</a> <a href="http://www.baptisttheology.org/book-reviews/baptist-ways-a-history/">have noted</a>, the Conservative Resurgence in the SBC also receives scant coverage, appearing only in summary on pages 414–415.</p>
<p>Occasionally, the book suggests that an emphasis on biblical literalism results in erratic or erroneous conclusions. An early example of this pattern occurs in the treatment of John Smyth, the early sixteenth-century Baptist. Smyth was certainly unstable, following a spiritual trajectory that parallels that of Roger Williams in America. Smyth began as an Anglican until he adopted Separatist views. Later, he founded the General Baptists along with Thomas Helwys by baptizing himself and then his own followers. This self-baptism brought criticism, and eventually Smyth repudiated his own baptism and sought admission into a nearby Mennonite sect. The book attributes Smyth’s restlessness to his commitment to the Bible: “His biblicism took him through many Protestant communities in a search for the fullest revelation available” (25). Smyth was undoubtedly a biblicist, but there are other explanations for his repudiation of his self-baptism. On occasion, the book suggests that biblicism leads to other negative results, which will disappoint conservative readers.</p>
<p>Other reviews have been mixed in their final appraisal of Leonard’s text, despite the unanimous acknowledgement that producing a one-volume Baptist history is a difficult task. As a potential course textbook, the work suffers from a lack of visual aids (a deficiency that equally applies to the competing volumes by Torbet and McBeth). Other complaints include the slightly negative treatment of more conservative Baptist traditions and the deliberately international focus of chapters 10–16. On the other hand, these two complaints illustrate and, to some degree, substantiate Leonard’s thesis that Baptists are a broadly differentiated sect. As a potential textbook for a course on Baptist history, I find Leonard’s text to be useful despite these perceived weaknesses. This is especially true for me as I teach the history of the Baptists outside of the United States of America. Although Leonard’s book should not be the only volume that students of the Baptists consult, I am convinced that it is a worthy member of the body of literature on the topic.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Textbooks for my Courses Next Semester]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/12/24/textbooks-for-my-courses-next-semester/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-24T14:53:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/12/24/textbooks-for-my-courses-next-semester</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This coming semester I’ll be teaching two courses, Church History Survey and Historical Books. I thought I’d post a few links here for anyone who might be planning to take one of these classes.</p>
<h2 id="th105-church-history-survey">Th105 Church History Survey</h2>
<p><a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/th105-2014/">Course website</a></p>
<p><em>Description:</em> Surveys the people, places and dates most important in understanding how the Holy Spirit has been saving, sanctifying and organizing people for the past two millennia.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/2013/12/noll.jpg" alt="Turning Points" /><figcaption>Turning Points</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><em>Textbook:</em> Noll, Mark A. <em>Turning Points: Decisive Moments in the History of Christianity.</em> 3rd ed. Baker Academic, 2012. ISBN 9780801039966.</p>
<p>Available for purchase here:</p>
<ul>
<li>eBook: <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B0085BAEIO/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B0085BAEIO&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon Kindle</a></li>
<li>Paperback: <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=039966">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="su401-historical-books">Su401 Historical Books</h2>
<p><a href="http://blogs.duncanjohnson.ca/su401-2014/">Course website</a></p>
<p><em>Description:</em> Overviews Joshua through Esther, emphasizing chronology and historical background. Highlights the introduction to each book (date of composition, author, occasion &amp; purpose, and recipients) and themes. Discusses contemporary application.</p>
<figure>
<img src="/images/2013/12/hamilton.jpg" alt="Handbook on the Historical Books" /><figcaption>Handbook on the Historical Books</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Hamilton, Victor P. <em>Handbook on the Historical Books: Joshua, Judges, Ruth, Samuel, Kings, Chronicles, Ezra-Nehemiah, Esther.</em> Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 2008. ISBN 9780801036149.</p>
<p>Available for purchase here:</p>
<ul>
<li>ebook: <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/B00CFKX6I6/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=390961&amp;creativeASIN=B00CFKX6I6&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Amazon Kindle</a></li>
<li>Paperback: <a href="http://www.christianbook.com/Christian/Books/product?event=AFF&amp;p=1178855&amp;item_no=036149">Christian Book Distributors</a></li>
</ul>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hoehner on Ephesians 4:4-6]]></title>
    <link href="http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/11/03/hoehner-on-ephesians-4-4-6/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T14:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://duncanjohnson.ca/blog/2013/11/03/hoehner-on-ephesians-4-4-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0801026148/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=330641&amp;creativeASIN=0801026148&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20"><img src="/images/2013/11/hoehner.jpg" alt="Hoehner on Ephesians" /></a></p>
<p>Today in my Adult Bible study class at <a href="http://www.meadowlandsbaptist.ca/">Meadowlands Baptist Church</a> we discussed these verses in Ephesians 4:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><sup>NKJ</sup> <strong>Ephesians 4:4-6</strong> There is one body and one Spirit, just as you were called in one hope of your calling; <sup>5</sup> one Lord, one faith, one baptism; <sup>6</sup> one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I found <a href="http://www.amazon.ca/gp/product/0801026148/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=15121&amp;creative=330641&amp;creativeASIN=0801026148&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=duncanjohns04-20">Hoehner</a> to be helpful in unpacking Paul’s meaning in these verses, so I decided to share his comments on these verses.</p>
<!-- more -->

<blockquote>
<p><strong>4:4.</strong> The sevenfold use of “one” (εἷς, μία, ἕν) emphasizes unity.</p>
<p>First, there is one body (ἓν σῶμα), which refers to the universal church already discussed (1:23; 2:16; 3:5–6). … it is not that Gentiles become Jews, as in the OT, nor Jews become Gentiles, but that unbelieving Jews and Gentiles become one body of believers when they place their faith in the work of Christ at Calvary. They are no longer two entities but one.</p>
<p>Second, there is the one Spirit (ἓν πνεῦμα) referring to the Holy Spirit. …</p>
<p>Third, there is one hope.With this clause Paul breaks from the pattern of verses 4a and 5–6 and refers back to the call mentioned in verse 1. He does this in order to give a conceptual framework on which the rest of the exhortation is based. … The noun ἐλπίς, “hope,” was discussed in 1:18 and was defined as eager expectation of the outworking of God’s plan. The hope presented in Ephesians is the reality that all things will be headed up in Christ (1:9) and though the believers are presently seated with Christ, in the future they will be displayed in heaven as trophies of his grace (2:7). Further, they have been brought near to God, united into one body in Christ and reconciled to God (2:11–3:13). Before this they were without hope and without God in the world (2:12). Hence, there is the element of objective hope which is laid up for the believers (cf. Col 1:5; Rom 8:24), and this serves as the basis of the subjective hope. Hope for believers is not the world’s “hope so” but the absolute certainty that God will deliver what he has promised.</p>
<p>In conclusion, then, the elements of unity are portrayed in the one body, the one Spirit, and the one hope of their calling. The third person of the Trinity is the unifier in this verse.</p>
<p><strong>4:5.</strong> Fourth, there is one Lord. In the previous verse the third person of the Trinity was discussed, Paul now considers the second person, Christ. The word κύριος logically refers to Christ since Paul has just discussed the Holy Spirit in verse 4 and will discuss the Father in the next verse. Christ is the “one Lord” who provided redemption (1:7), hope (1:12), and headship over the church (1:22–23).</p>
<p>Fifth, there is one faith. The “one faith” does not have reference to an objective faith, the body of truth believed by Christians … as some propose, but rather to the subjective faith which is exercised by all Christians in Christ their Lord (cf. Col 2:7). … In the first chapter of this book, Paul mentions that the Ephesians had expressed their faith when they heard the message (1:13) and that their faith in the Lord Jesus was widely known (1:15). Thus, it is the one faith in the one Lord.</p>
<p>Sixth, there is one baptism. This phrase has caused some debate. There are two major views and a third should be considered. First, most commentators think it has reference to water baptism. … Second, some consider it to be a reference to the Spirit’s baptism. … A third option that needs to be considered is that it refers metaphorically to the believer’s baptism into Christ’s death, speaking of the believer’s union with Christ in his death and resurrection. … This same concept is seen in other NT passages (Rom 6:1–11; Gal. 3:27; Col 2:12). Furthermore, it fits well with the context, for the believer’s baptism into Christ signifies union with Christ (Rom 6:5) and it occurs at the time of conversion (Rom 6:2–4). This inward reality is all too often missed. It serves as the basis of the outward ritual. Hence, the “one baptism” most likely refers to the internal reality of having been baptized into (identified with) the “one Lord” by means of the “one faith” mentioned in this verse.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In conclusion, there is unity in the one Lord in whom believers place their one faith expressed in one baptism signifying their identification in his death and resurrection. This verse revolves around the second person of the Trinity.</p>
<p><strong>4:6.</strong> “one God and Father of all.” This is the third triad and it speaks of God the Father. This marks the climax, for God is the one unifying factor in both testaments, in spite of the fact that many gods are honored in the world. … God is further described as the God and Father “of all,” which refers not to all humans but to all believers (John 1:12; Gal 3:26). This is substantiated in the present context because Paul is exhorting Christians, and not all humans, to preserve the unity.</p>
<p>Regarding the further identification of God, there are three parts. First, he is over (ἐπί) all, indicating his sovereign position over all believers. … Second, not only is God sovereign in all believers’ lives, he also works through (δία) all of them. Here the emphasis is on God’s immanence. … Finally, God is in all believers (ἐν πᾶσιν̓ ἡμῖν). This signifies the indwelling Spirit …, his intimate presence. <a href="#fn1" class="footnoteRef" id="fnref1"><sup>1</sup></a></p>
</blockquote>
<section class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Harold Hoehner, <em>Ephesians: an Exegetical Commentary</em> (Grand Rapids, MI: Baker Academic, 2002), 513–520.<a href="#fnref1">↩</a></p></li>
</ol>
</section>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
